<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true Catholike Collected out of the oracles, and psalteries of the Holy Ghost. for instruction, and deuotion.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 146 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100465</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836305</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836305</idno>
            <idno type="VID">565</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 565)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1355:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true Catholike Collected out of the oracles, and psalteries of the Holy Ghost. for instruction, and deuotion.</title>
                  <author>Fernández de Ribera, Rodrigo, 1579-1631.</author>
                  <author>Packer, Thomas, fl. 1628-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 256, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Miller] for E. Blackmore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Preface translated out of Rodrigo Fernández de Ribera, by Thomas Packer--STC.</note>
                  <note>K3 is a separate title page, with same imprint, reading: Psalteries of the Holy Ghost.</note>
                  <note>M5 is a separate title page, with same imprint, reading: Psalmes in sicknesse.</note>
                  <note>Errata on recto of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show thorugh; some pages stained, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 4831.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Quotations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  English. --  Selections --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Devotional use of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE TRVE CATHOLIKE Collected out of the Oracles, and Pſalteries of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>for
<list>
                        <item>Inſtruction, and</item>
                        <item>Deuotion.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 TIM. 2.4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>God will haue all men to be ſaued, and to come to the knowledge of the truth.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>IOH. 14.17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The world cannot receiue the ſpirit of truth, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 COR. 2.10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The ſpirit ſearcheth all things; yea the deepe things of God.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>EPHES. 5.9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>For the fruit of the ſpirit is in all goodneſſe, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and truth.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for E. BLACKMORE. 1628.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE OF DOCTOR FRA. RIBERA
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">In Coment. in Amos: Prophet:</note> touching the Excellency, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity &amp; profit of
<hi>finding the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT there is no ſtudie either more Excellent, more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table: or more worthy of Man, then the ſtudie of the holy Scriptures; hee <pb facs="tcp:565:3"/> ſhall beſt know and iudge that applyeth himſelfe wholy thereunto; and ſhal perceiue that man to bee worthily called bleſſed,
<hi>Which meditateth in the law of God day and night.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 1, 2.</note> I doe verily confeſſe that all the ſacred bookes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, are wrapped and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbred with many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties; by which (as it were by certaine ſtrict keepers of a moſt ſtately Temple) The holy Ghoſt hath ſtraitly prohibited the acceſſe and miſteries vnto prophane and proud men; and that it is rightly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <pb facs="tcp:565:3"/> of them which <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> is reported to haue ſaid when he hapned vpon <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus</hi> bookes of nature: <hi>That thoſe things which hee vnderſtood ſeemed excellent vnto him; and that hee thought ſo alſo of them which hee vnderſtood not; but that it was needfull to haue an Interpreter to them.</hi> No where can you ſee more euidently, no where can it more appeare which is ſpoken in the old Greeke prouerbe; <hi>Thoſe things which are excellent are difficult:</hi> Or, that ſaying which paſſeth far &amp; neare from <hi>Heſiodus</hi> concerning vertue, <pb facs="tcp:565:4"/> 
                     <hi>That it is ſcituate in a ſteepe and high place, and that it hath a paſſage in the beginning, hard, and full of paine and labour.</hi> But doubtleſſe although the labour be great, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall, it doth ſufficiently recompence with profit, the paine with eaſe; the earneſt endeauour of the minde with reſt. For although they ſeeme to haue much hardneſſe; yet without doubt they haue farre more of true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect delight. For how great a matter is it to bee led by a King into a wine-Cellar?<note place="margin">Cant. 2.4.</note> For Charity to
<pb facs="tcp:565:4"/> be rightly ordered? How great a matter is it to ſucke thoſe breſts better then wine, ſauoring ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the beſt oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?<note place="margin">Cant. 1.2.</note> To hold wiſedome (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) among thoſe that bee per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.6.</note> Yet not the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world, nor of the Princes of this world which come to nought; but the wiſedome of God in a miſterie, which none of the Princes of this world knew?<note place="margin">7.</note>
                     <note place="margin">8.</note> To be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the diſtribution of heauenly treaſures? <hi>To behold the glory of God with open face?</hi> Certainely the <pb facs="tcp:565:5"/> ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared with the future glory, which (when wee well vnderſtand the ſacred bookes) ſhall be reuealed in vs. But the men of our time are quicke and ready to other ſtudies, vnto theſe for the moſt part they are ſlow and do ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that theſe are to bee left to idle men, and ſuch as tarrie at home, or elſe vnto Preachers. Whereby it happens that ſuch as are vnfit for ſermons, though they haue leaſure enough, doe rather beſtow their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and endeauour in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <pb facs="tcp:565:5"/> other matter.</p>
                  <p>How much the holy Scriptures doe profit prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, I haue often ſaid; and how greatly they ſtand in neede of them which are excerciſed in Schoole diſputations, I could ſay, and perchance will hereafter ſhew. Now this I auouch, that (albeit theſe Scriptures bee moſt profitable to helpe others) they iudge very ill, who thinke they are to bee ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died onely for other mens ſakes. For if we reade with great profit the bookes of the holy fathers, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned men which <pb facs="tcp:565:6"/> are called, and are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and by reading them doe finde our ſelues much bettered; ſhall there bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny book ſo ſpirituall which may bee compared with thoſe which the ſpirit of God it ſelfe (by the choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, and wiſeſt men) hath deliuered vnto vs? If the ſmall brookes doe helpe and (as it were) ſatisfie; what ſhall that great <hi>Riuer</hi> doe which
<hi>Ezechiell</hi> ſaw,<note place="margin">Ezec. 47.1.</note> iſſuing forth vnder the threſhold of the Lords houſe? which he could not goe through becauſe the waters of that deepe riuer were riſen ſo that they
<pb facs="tcp:565:6"/> could not bee paſſed ouer. And when I had returned,<note place="margin">5.</note> ſaid he, behold, at the bank of the riuer were very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny trees on either ſide,<note place="margin">7.</note> what are thoſe many trees on either ſide the banke of the riuer, but the ancient writers ioyned to the Law and the Prophets, and the new writers, who ſitting together by the ſtreames of the Euangeliſts and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; doe alwayes waxe greene as moſt beautifull trees and abound with pleaſant fruite: the riuer is the ſame, becauſe it is the ſame author of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the ſcope the <pb facs="tcp:565:7"/> ſame, but the ages and times diuers, which are reſembled by both the bankes.</p>
                  <p>Of theſe trees and of theſe waters it is ſaid, and he ſhall be like a tree <hi>plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the riuers of waters that bringeth forth his fruite in his ſeaſon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note>
                     <hi>his leafe alſo ſhall not fall away, and whatſoeuer be doth it ſhall proſper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I was wont to maruaile with my ſelfe as often as I did reade in Saint <hi>Ierome,</hi> that the ſtudy of the Scriptures had wonderfull power to change the <pb facs="tcp:565:7"/> minde of man, to quench the deſires of the fleſh, to procure the contempt of the world, and briefly to gaine all kinde of vertue; vntill I perceiued hee ſpake thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee had made triall in himſelfe; and that it is a wrong, not to belieue him that hath experience. <hi>Hee that beleeueth not,</hi> let him firſt reade the Scripture, not as though hee would interpret it to others, but to be turned wholy to his owne profit: let him medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate therein day and night; he ſhall feele a ſtony heart <pb facs="tcp:565:8"/> to bee mollified, a cold heart to be inflamed, with heauenly fire: <hi>for the words of the Lord are like fire,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er. 23.29.</note> 
                     <hi>and as a hammer that breaketh the rocke in peeces.</hi> He ſhall perceiue the loue of the world to vaniſh away, the deſire of eternall good things to bee ſtirred vp in himſelfe, his minde filled with a certaine incredible delight; which he that felt it cried out,
<hi>how ſweete are thy words vnto my taſte?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal.
119.103.</note> 
                     <hi>yea ſweeter then hony to my mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O wiſdome guide of the heauenly life, teacher of <pb facs="tcp:565:8"/> vertues, bane of vices, fountaine of light, expeller of darkeneſſe, what ſhould wee, nay what ſhould the whole life of man be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thou art the companion in labour, thou art the comforter in aduerſitie, the ouerſeere and guide in proſperitie, the inſtructer of youth, the foundation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the moſt ſweet reſt of old age. Come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs aſcend vp to the hill of the Lord,<note place="margin">Iſa.
2.3.</note> to the houſe of the GOD of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and he will teach vs his wayes, and wee ſhall <pb facs="tcp:565:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> walke in his pathes, and let not obſcuritie diſcourage vs.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:9"/>
                  <head>The heads con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>A Preparation. <hi>Fol. 2</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>God. <hi>Fol. 5</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Scriptures. <hi>Fol. 12</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Church. <hi>Fol. 23</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Traditions. <hi>Fol. 28</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Images. <hi>Fol. 38</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Inuocation. <hi>Fol. 47</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:565:10"/>Adoration. <hi>Fol. 53</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith. <hi>Fol. 61</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Repentance. <hi>Fol. 64</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Confeſsion. <hi>Fol. 68</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith and workes. <hi>Fol. 73</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Iuſtification. <hi>Fol. 81</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faſting. <hi>Fol. 90</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Meates. <hi>Fol. 98</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Loue and Charity. <hi>Fol. 105</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Prayer. <hi>Fol. 111</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>One Mediator. <hi>Fol. 116</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Our propitiation, Purgatory, and ſatisfaction. <hi>Fol.
118</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sinnes. <hi>Fol. 124.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Will. <hi>Fol. 130</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hypocriſie. <hi>Fol. 135</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Riches. <hi>Fol. 139</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Patience. <hi>Fol. 145</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Humility. <hi>Fol. 149</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The holy Euchariſt. <hi>Fol. 155</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:565:10"/>The happineſſe of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.
<hi>Fol. 164</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The vanitie of the world. <hi>Fol. 167</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The end of the world. <hi>Fol. 171</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Iudgement. <hi>Fol. 179</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <div type="list_of_Psalms">
                     <head>Pſalmes.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Of Confeſsion. <hi>Fol. 200</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Of contrition. <hi>Fol. 203</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>For remiſsion. <hi>Fol. 206</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>For mercie and direction. <hi>Fol. 209</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>For vnderſtanding. <hi>Fol. 212</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>In trouble. <hi>Fol. 215.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>For deliuerance. <hi>Fol. 217</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:565:11"/>Againſt our Enemies. <hi>Fol.
220</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Of Confidence in Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. <hi>Fol. 225</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Acknowledging Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. <hi>Fol. 228</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Magnifying Gods mercie, and goodneſſe. <hi>Fol.
233</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Of praiſe. <hi>Fol. 236</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="sickness" type="Psalms">
                     <head>Pſalmes in Sickneſſe.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1</hi> Pſalme in ſickneſſe. <hi>Fol.
242</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2</hi> Pſalme. <hi>Fol. 244</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3</hi> Pſalme. <hi>Fol. 246</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4</hi> Pſalme. <hi>Fol. 248</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>A Prayer. <hi>Fol. 252</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The ſoules Comfort. <hi>Fol. 254</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:565:11"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:12"/>
                  <head>AN EPISTLE GENERALL.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Beloued,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> THe Spirit ſpeaketh expreſſely, that in the latter times ſome ſhall depart from the Faith, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing heed to ſeducing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and doctrines of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Speaking lyes in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, hauing their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſeared with a hot iron.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Forbidding to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <pb facs="tcp:565:13"/> and commanding to abſtaine from meats which God hath created to bee receiued with thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and know the truth:</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim 4.</note>4. For euery creature of God is good, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be refuſed, if it be receiued with thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. For it is ſanctified by the word of God, and prayer.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note>10. There are many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly, and vaine-talkers, and deceiuers.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopped, who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert whole houſes, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <pb facs="tcp:565:13"/> things which they ought not for filthy lucres ſake.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Giue not heed to Iewiſh fables, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of men that turne from the truth.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.</note> They are of the world, therefore ſpeake they of the world, and the world heareth them.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. We are of God; hee that knoweth God, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs; hee that is not of God, heareth not vs: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by know wee the ſpirit of truth, and the ſpirit of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Beware,<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> leſt any man ſpoile you through phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, <pb facs="tcp:565:14"/> and vaine deceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, &amp; not after Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. For in him dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head bodily.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. And wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate in him which is the head of all principalitie, &amp; power.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note>14. Striue not about words to no profit, but to the ſubuerting of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Fooliſh and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned queſtions auoide, knowing that they do gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtrifes.</p>
                  <p n="27">
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note>27. Stand faſt in one
<pb facs="tcp:565:14"/> ſpirit with one mind, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing together for the faith of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. And in nothing ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by your aduerſaries, which is to them an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent token of perdition; but to you of ſaluation, &amp; that of God.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. For vnto you it is giuen in the behalfe of Chriſt, not onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</p>
                  <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">Col. 3.</note> Put on therefore (as the elect of God, holy, and beloued) bowells of mercies, kindneſſe, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of mind, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, long ſuffering.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <pb facs="tcp:565:15"/>13. Forbearing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forgiuing one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, if any man haue a quarrell againſt any, euen as Chriſt forgaue you, ſo alſo do ye.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. And aboue all things put on charitie, which is the bond of perfectneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. And let the peace of God rule in your hearts to the which alſo yee are called in one body, and be ye thankfull.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. And whatſoeuer ye do in word or deed, do all in the name of the Lord Ieſus, giuing thankes to God and the Father by him.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb facs="tcp:565:15"/>6.<note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> Bee carefull for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but in euery thing by prayer, and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with thankſgiuing, let your requeſts bee made knowne vnto God.</p>
                  <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> Continue in the faith grounded and ſetled, and be not mooued away from the hope of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which ye haue heard, and which was preached to euery creature which is vnder heauen.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 That ye henceforth bee no more children toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed too and fro,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about with euery wind of doctrine, by the ſleight of men, and cunning craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:565:16"/> whereby they lye in wait to deceiue.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. But ſpeaking the truth in loue, may grow vp into him in al things which is the head, euen Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note>9. And this I pray, that your loue may abound yet more and more in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp; in all iudgement.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. That yee may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue things that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, that ye may be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and without offence till the day of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Being filled with the fruites of righteouſneſſe, which are by Ieſus Chriſt, vnto the glorie and praiſe of God. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="oracles">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:565:16"/>
                  <head>ORACLES AND PSALTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIES OF THE HOLY GHOST.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat Nation is there ſo great,<note place="margin">Deut.
4.8.</note> that hath Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, &amp; Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo righteous, as all this Law, which I ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you this day?</p>
                  <p>This is the way;<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.21.</note> walke ye in it, when ye turne to the right hand, and when ye turne to the left.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:565:17"/>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 12.34.</note>Thou ſhalt not adde thereto, nor diminiſh from it.</p>
                  <div n="preparation" type="oracles">
                     <head>Preparation.</head>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">Amos 4.</note>12. PRepare to meet thy God ô Iſrael.</p>
                     <p n="23">
                        <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.</note>23. I will teach you the good and the right way:</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Only feare the Lord, and ſerue him in truth with all your heart.</p>
                     <p n="23">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>33. Seeke yee firſt the kingdome of God, and his righteouſneſſe, and all things ſhall be added vnto you.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note>4. Delight thy ſelfe alſo in the Lord, and he ſhall <pb n="3" facs="tcp:565:17"/> giue thee the deſires of thine heart.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Pro. 3.</note> Truſt in the Lord with all thine heart, and leane not vnto thine owne vnderſtanding.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. In all thy wayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, and hee ſhall direct thy paths.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.</note> He ſhall couer thee with his feathers, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his wing ſhalt thou truſt, his truth ſhall be thy ſhield and buckler.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">34.</note> O taſt and ſee that the Lord is good, bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">146.</note> Happy is he that hath the God of Iacob for his helpe, whoſe hope is in the <pb n="4" facs="tcp:565:18"/> Lord his God.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.</note>14. Waite on the Lord, be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen thine heart: Waite I ſay on the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">125.</note>1. They that truſt in the Lord ſhall bee as Mount Sion, which cannot bee remoued, but abideth for euer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. As the mountaines are round about Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſo the Lord is round about his people; from henceforth euen for euer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="God" type="oracles">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:565:18"/>
                     <head>God.</head>
                     <p n="8">8. HEare ô my people,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8
1.</note> and I will teſtifie vnto thee; ô Iſrael, if thou wilt hearken vnto me:</p>
                     <p n="9">9. There ſhall no ſtrange God bee in thee, neither ſhalt thou worſhip any ſtrange God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Iſa. 43.</note> For I am the Lord thy God, the holy One of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, thy Sauiour.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Before mee there was no God formed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal there be after me.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. I, euen I am the Lord; and beſides me, there is no Sauiour.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:565:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <note place="margin">44.</note>6. I am the firſt, and I am the laſt, and beſides me there is no God.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Thus ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer, and he that formed thee from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> wombe; I am the Lord that maketh all things, that ſtretcheth foorth the heauens alone, that ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth abroad the earth by my ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">48.</note>12. Hearken vnto me O Iacob, and Iſrael my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; I am he, I am the firſt, and I am the laſt.</p>
                     <p n="49">
                        <note place="margin">Act. 7.</note>49. Heauen is my Throne, and earth is my footeſtoole.</p>
                     <p n="22">
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 45.</note>22. Looke vnto me, and <pb n="7" facs="tcp:565:19"/> be ye ſaued all the ends of the earth: for I am God, and there is none elſe.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> To vs there is but one God, the Father of whom are all things, and we in him; and one Lord Ieſus Chriſt by whom are all things, and we by him.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> There is one God &amp; Father of all, who is aboue all, and through all, and in you all.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. In him we liue,<note place="margin">Act 17.</note> and moue, and haue our being, for we are all his of ſpring.</p>
                     <p n="29">29. Foraſmuch then as wee are the of-ſpring of God, wee ought not to thinke that the Godhead <pb n="8" facs="tcp:565:20"/> is like vnto gold, or ſiluer, or ſtone grauen by
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and mans deuice.</p>
                     <p n="30">30. And the times of this ignorance God win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at; but now comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all men euery where to repent.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. Becauſe he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a day in the which he will iudge the world in righteouſneſſe, by that man whom he hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whereof hee hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aſſurance vnto all men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">Reuel. 4.</note>11. Thou art worthy O Lord to receiue glory, and honour, and power, for <pb n="9" facs="tcp:565:20"/> thou haſt created all things, and for thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they are and were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. This is eternall life,<note place="margin">Ioh.
17.</note> that we might know thee the onely true God, and Ieſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</p>
                     <p n="27">27.<note place="margin">Pſal 73.</note> They that are farre from thee ſhal periſh; thou haſt deſtroyed all them that goe a whoring from thee.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">16.</note> Their ſorrowes ſhall be multiplyed that haſten after another God.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">96.</note> All the Gods of the Nations are Idols, but the Lord made the heauens.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:565:21"/>6. Honour and Maieſty are before him; ſtrength and beauty are in his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">89.</note>6. For who in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen can be compared vnto the Lord? who among the ſonnes of the mightie can be likened vnto the Lord?</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">95.</note>7. He is our God, and wee are the people of his paſture, and the ſheepe of his hands.</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">Ioſh. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>16. God forbid that we ſhould forſake the Lord, to ſerue other gods.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. Put away the ſtrange gods which are among you &amp; incline your hearts vnto the Lord God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</p>
                     <p n="24">
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:565:21"/>24. The Lord our God will we ſerue, and his voice will we obey.</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.</note> The Lord is a God of iudgement, bleſſed are they that waite for him.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.</note> They that ſeeke the Lord, ſhall not want any good thing.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. For he is gracious,<note place="margin">Ioel
2.</note> and mercifull, ſlow to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of great kindneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="50">50.<note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> And his mercy is on them that feare him from generation to generation.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">Pſal 33.</note> Bleſſed is the nation whoſe God is the Lord: and the people whom hee hath choſen for his owne inheritance.</p>
                     <p n="36">
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:565:22"/>
                        <note place="margin">Rom.
11.</note>36. For of him, and through him, and to him are all things: To whom be glory for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="scriptures" type="oracles">
                     <head>The holy Scriptures.</head>
                     <p n="29">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note>29. YE doe erre, not knowing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor the power of God.</p>
                     <p n="29">
                        <note place="margin">Ier. 23.</note>29. Is not my word like as a fire, ſaith the Lord? &amp; like a hammer that brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the rocke in peeces?</p>
                     <p n="39">
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note>39. Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for in them ye think yee haue eternall life; and they are they which teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie of me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:565:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Receiue with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the ingrafted word, which is able to ſaue your ſoules.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. Theſe are written,<note place="margin">Ioh.
20.</note> that ye might beleeue that Ieſus is the Chriſt the Son of God: and that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, yee might haue life through his name.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.</note> For whatſoeuer things were written aforetime, were written for our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that we through pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and comfort of the Scriptures might haue hope.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note> If any man teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, and conſent not to wholſome words, euen <pb n="14" facs="tcp:565:23"/> the words of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which is according to godlineſſe.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. He is proud, knowing nothing, but doting about queſtions, and ſtrifes of words, whereof commeth enuie, ſtrife, raylings, euill ſurmiſes;</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Peruerſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds, and deſtitute of the truth, ſuppoſing that gaine is godlineſſe; from ſuch with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw thy ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="31">
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note>31. If ye continue in my word, then are yee my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples indeed.</p>
                     <p n="32">32. And ye ſhall know <pb n="15" facs="tcp:565:23"/> the truth, and the truth ſhall make you free.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Pro. 8.</note> All the words of my mouth are in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: there is nothing fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or peruerſe in them.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. They are all plaine to him that vnderſtandeth, and right to them that find knowledge.</p>
                     <p n="47">47. He that is of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> heareth Gods words.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">2. Ioh. 1.</note> Whoſoeuer tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth, and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God: he that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the doctrine of Chriſt, hee hath both the Father and the Sonne.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. If there come any <pb n="16" facs="tcp:565:24"/> vnto you, and bring not this doctrine receiue him not into your houſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bid him God ſpeed.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">2 Chron. 17.</note>9. The Leuites and the Prieſts ſent by <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> taught in Iuda, &amp; had the booke of the Law of the Lord with them; and went about throughout all the Cities of Iuda, and taught the people.</p>
                     <p n="31">
                        <note place="margin">34.</note>31. <hi>Ioſiah</hi> made a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant before the Lord to walke after the Lord, and to keepe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; his teſtimonies, and his Statutes, with all his heart, and with all his ſoule, to performe the <pb n="17" facs="tcp:565:24"/> words of the couenant which are written in this booke.</p>
                     <p n="32">32. And hee cauſed all that were preſent in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem &amp; Beniamin to ſtand to it: And the Inhabitants of Ieruſalem did accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the couenant of God, the God of their fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                     <p n="35">35.<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi> alſo and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> continued in Antioch teaching and preaching the word of the Lord with many others alſo.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.<note place="margin">17.</note> The Iewes of Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a were more noble then thoſe in Theſſalonica, in that they receiued the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:565:25"/> word with all readineſſe of minde, and ſearched the Scriptures daily whether thoſe things were ſo.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. Therefore many of them belieued; alſo of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable women which were Greekes, and of men not a fewe.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Acts. 17.</note>1. When <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> had paſſed throrough Amphipolis &amp; Apolloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, they came to Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica, where was a Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of the Iewes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. And <hi>Paul</hi> as his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was, went in vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and three Sabbath dayes reaſoned with them out of the Scriptures.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:565:25"/>17.<note place="margin">Ephe.
6.</note> Take the helmet of ſaluation and the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> The word of the Lord is quick, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſharper then any two edged ſword, piercing euen to the deuiding aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſoule and ſpirit, and of the ioynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and intents of the heart.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> As new borne babes deſire the ſincere milke of the word, that yee may grow thereby.</p>
                     <p n="15">15.<note place="margin">1</note> The word of the Lord endureth for euer, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:565:26"/> and this is the word which by the Goſpell is preached vnto you.</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note>16. All Scripture is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, for reproofe, for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. That the man of God may be perfect, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly furniſhed vnto all good works.</p>
                     <p n="20">
                        <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note>20. No prophecie of the Scripture is of any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate interpretation.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. For the prophecie came not in old time by the will of man; But holy men of God ſpake as they <pb n="21" facs="tcp:565:26"/> were moued by the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> The law of the Lord is perfect conuerting the ſoule, the teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, making wiſe the ſimple.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">12.</note> The words of the Lord are pure words, as ſiluer tryed in a furnace of earth purified ſeuen times.</p>
                     <p n="104">104.<note place="margin">119.</note> Through thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts I get vnderſtanding: Therfore I hate euery falſe way.</p>
                     <p n="100">100. I vnderſtand more then the ancients; becauſe I keepe thy precepts.</p>
                     <p n="118">118. Thou haſt trodden downe all them that erre
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:565:27"/> from thy ſtatutes for their deceit is falſhood.</p>
                     <p n="105">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>105. Thy word is a lampe vnto my feet and a light vnto my path.</p>
                     <p n="165">165. Great peace haue they which loue thy law; And nothing ſhall offend them.</p>
                     <p n="130">130. The entrance of thy words giueth light; it giueth vnderſtanding to the ſimple.</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">Phil 3.</note>16. Whereto we haue already attained, let vs walke by the ſame rule, let vs minde the ſame thing.</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note>16. As many as walke according to this rule, Peace be on them, and <pb n="23" facs="tcp:565:27"/> mercie, and vpon the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="church" type="oracles">
                     <head>The Church.</head>
                     <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5</note> CHriſt is the head of the Church, and he is the Saviour of the bodie.</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> Hee is the head of the body the Church who is the beginning, the firſt borne from the dead, that in all things he might haue the preheminence.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. I now reioyce in my ſufferings for you, and fill vp that which is behind of the afflictions of Chriſt in my fleſh, for his bodies <pb n="24" facs="tcp:565:28"/> ſake which is the Church.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note>14. The bodie is not one member but many.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. GOD hath ſet the members euery one of them in the body as it hath pleaſed him.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. And if they were all one member, where were the bodie.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. But now are they many members, yet but one body.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. God hath tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the bodie together, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more abundant honour to that part which lacked.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. That there ſhould be no ſchiſme in the body:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:565:28"/> but that the members ſhould haue the ſame care one for another.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. And whether one member ſuffer al the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſuffer with it: or one member bee honoured all the members reioyce with it.</p>
                     <p n="27">27 Now ye are the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, and members in particular.</p>
                     <p n="25">25.<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> Chriſt loued the Church, and gaue himſelfe for it.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. That he might ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, and cleanſe it, with the waſhing of water, by the word.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. That he might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <pb n="26" facs="tcp:565:29"/> it to himſelfe a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Church, not hauing ſpotte, or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing: but that it ſhould he holy and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blemiſh.</p>
                     <p n="15">
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note>15. The Church of God is the houſe of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, the pillar, and ground of truth.</p>
                     <p n="47">
                        <note place="margin">Acts 2.</note>47. The Lord added to the Church dayly ſuch as ſhould be ſaued.</p>
                     <p n="42">42. And they continued ſtedfaſt in the Apoſtles doctrine, and fellowſhip: and in breaking of bread, and in prayers.</p>
                     <p n="27">
                        <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note>27. My ſheepe heare my voyce, and I know <pb n="27" facs="tcp:565:29"/> them, and they follow me.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. And I giue vnto them eternall life; and they ſhal neuer periſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any man plucke them out of my hand.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. A ſtranger will they not follow, but flie from him: for they know not the voice of ſtrangers.</p>
                     <p n="37">37.<note place="margin">Ioh. 18.</note> Euery one that is of the trueth, heareth my voice.</p>
                     <p n="19">19.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> Now therefore ye are no more ſtrangers, and forreyners, but fellow Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens with the ſaints, and of the houſhold of God.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. And are built vpon the foundation of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <pb n="28" facs="tcp:565:30"/> and Prophets, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt being the chiefe corner ſtone.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. In whom all the building fitly framed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, groweth vnto an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly temple in the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. In whom you alſo are builded together, for an habitation of GOD, through the Spirit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="traditions" type="oracles">
                     <head>Traditions.</head>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">Col. 2.</note>8. BEware leſt any man ſpoile you through Philoſohie, and vaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, after the tradition of men, after the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:565:30"/>17.<note place="margin">2. Pet.
2.</note> Theſe are wells without water; cloudes that are caried with a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, to whom the myſt of darkneſſe is reſerued for euer.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. My ſpeech,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.</note> &amp; my prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, was not with inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing words, of mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome but in demonſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſpirit, and of power.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. That your faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſedome of Men, but in the power of God.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. We ſpeake wiſdome among them that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; yet not the wiſdome of this world, nor of the Princes of this world that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:565:31"/> come to nought.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. But wee ſpeake the wiſdome of God in a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; euen the hidden wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which God ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before the world, to our glory.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note>19. For the wiſdome of this world is fooliſhneſſe with God: for it is written, he taketh the wiſe in their owne craftineſſe.</p>
                     <p n="28">
                        <note place="margin">Ier. 23.</note>28. The Prophet that hath a dreame, let him tell a dreame; and he that hath my word, let him ſpeake my word faithfully: what is the chaffe to the wheate ſaith the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note>6. Take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware <pb n="31" facs="tcp:565:31"/> of the leauen of the Phariſes, and of the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces.</p>
                     <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.</note> Foraſmuch as this people drawe neere mee with their mouth, and with their lipps doe honor me, but haue remoued their heart farre from mee, and their feare towards me is taught by the precepts of men.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. The wiſedome of their wiſe men ſhal periſh, and the vnderſtanding of their prudent men ſhall be hid.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Mar. 7.</note> In vaine they do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me, teaching for doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines the commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts <pb n="32" facs="tcp:565:32"/> of men.</p>
                     <p n="20">
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.</note>20. To the law, and to the Teſtimony: If they ſpeake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">66.</note>3. They haue choſen their owne waies, and their ſoule delighteth in their abhominations.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <note place="margin">Ier. 6.</note>10. Their eare is vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, and they cannot hearken; the word of the Lord is to them a reproch; they haue no delight in it.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Ier 2.</note>13. They haue forſaken the fountaine of liuing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hewed them out ciſternes, broken ciſternes, that can hold no water.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:565:32"/>8. But though we,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.</note> or an Angell from Heauen preach any other Goſpell to you, then that which we haue preached vnto you, let him be accurſed.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. The Goſpell which was preached of mee, was not after man.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. For I neither recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it of man, neither was I taught it but by the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="17">17.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.</note> We are not as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which corrupt the word of God; but as of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, but as of God, in the ſight of God ſpeake we in Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">4.</note> Not walking in craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, <pb n="34" facs="tcp:565:33"/> nor handling the word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſtation of the truth; commending our ſelues vnto euery mans conſcience in the ſight of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. But if our Goſpell be hid, it is hid to them that are loſt.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. In whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds of men which beleeue not, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt, who is the image of God, ſhould ſhine vnto them.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">Ezek 20.</note>18. Walke not in the ſtatutes of your Fathers, <pb n="35" facs="tcp:565:33"/> neither obſerue their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor defile your ſelues with their Idols.</p>
                     <p n="19">19.<note place="margin">Ezech 20.</note> I am the Lord your God, walke in my ſtatutes, and keepe my iudgements, and do them.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> Ye ſhall not adde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the word which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, neither ſhall you diminiſh ought from it; that yee may keepe the cammandements of the Lord your God, which I command you.</p>
                     <p n="32">32.<note place="margin">12.</note> What thing ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I command you, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue to do it; Thou ſhalt not adde thereto, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh from it.</p>
                     <p n="32">
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:565:34"/>
                        <note place="margin">Deut.
5.</note>32. Ye ſhall obſerue to doe as the Lord your God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded you, you ſhall not turne aſide to the right hand, or to the left.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">28.</note>14. Thou ſhalt not go aſide from any of the words which I command thee this day, to the right hand or to the left, to goe after other Gods to ſerue them.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Aske for the olde pathes,<note place="margin">Ier.
6.</note> where is the good way, and walke therein; and you ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules.</p>
                     <p n="39">
                        <note place="margin">Num. 15.</note>39. Remember all the commandements of the Lord and doe, them; and <pb n="37" facs="tcp:565:34"/> ſeeke not after your owne heart, and your owne eyes, after which ye vſe to goe a whoring.</p>
                     <p n="17">17.<note place="margin">Ier. 6.</note> Hearken to the ſound of the trumpet.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Mal. 4.</note> Remember yee the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> my ſeruant, which I commanded to you in Horeb for all Iſrael, with the ſtatutes, and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">Pro. 30.</note> Adde not thou vnto his words, leaſt he reproue thee, and thou be found a lier.</p>
                     <p n="15">15 Though it be but a mans couenant, yet,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> if it be confirmed, no man diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anulleth, or addeth therto.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:565:35"/>
                        <note place="margin">Reuel.
22.</note>18. I teſtifie vnto euery man that heareth the words of the Prophecie of this book; If any man ſhall adde vnto theſe things, God ſhall adde vnto him the plagues that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in this booke.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. And if any man ſhall take away from the words of the booke of this Prophecie; God ſhall take away his part out of the booke of life, and out of the holy citie, and from the things which are written in this booke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="images" type="oracles">
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:565:35"/>
                     <head>Images.</head>
                     <p n="21">21. LIttle children, keep your ſelues from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Leuit. 26.</note> Yee ſhall make you no Idols, nor grauen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, neither reare you vp a ſtanding Image, neither ſhall you ſet vp any Image of ſtone in your land to bow downe vnto it, for I am the Lord your God.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Deut. 5.</note> Thou ſhalt not make thee any grauen Image, or any likeneſſe of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the waters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the earth.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <pb n="40" facs="tcp:565:36"/>9. Thou ſhalt not bow downe thy ſelfe vnto them, nor ſerue them.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.</note>18. To whom will yee liken God? or what like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will yee compare vnto him?</p>
                     <p n="15">
                        <note place="margin">Deu. 4.</note>15. Ye ſaw no ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude on the day that the Lord ſpake vnto you in Horeb out of the middeſt of the fire.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. Ye heard the voice of the words, but ſaw no ſimilitude, onely ye heard a voice.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. And hee declared vnto you his couenant which hee commanded you to performe, euen ten <pb n="41" facs="tcp:565:36"/> commandements; and he wrote them vpon two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of ſtone.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. I am the Lord,<note place="margin">Iſa. 42.</note> that is my name, and my glory will I not giue to another, neither my praiſe to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Images.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">Ier. 10.</note> Euery founder is confounded by the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Image: for his moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Image is falſhood, and there is no breath in them.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. They are vanitie, and the worke of errours, in the time of their viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ſhall periſh.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. The ſtocke is a doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of vanities.</p>
                     <p n="29">29.<note place="margin">Iſa. 41.</note> Their moulten I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages <pb n="42" facs="tcp:565:37"/> are winde, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 97.</note>7. Confounded be all they that ſerue grauen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, that boaſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of Idols.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 44.</note>9. They that make a graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Image are al of them vanitie, and their delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things ſhall not profit; and they are their owne witneſſes, they ſee not, nor know, that they may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">45.</note>16. They ſhall be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and alſo confounded all of them; they ſhall goe to confuſion together that are makers of Idols.</p>
                     <p n="23">
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note>23. Take heede vnto
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:565:37"/> your ſelues, leaſt yee forget the couenant of the Lord your GOD which he made with you, and make you a grauen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or the likeneſſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which the Lord thy GOD hath forbidden thee.</p>
                     <p n="29">29.<note place="margin">Acts 17.</note> Wee ought not to thinke that the Godhead is like vnto gold, or ſiluer, or ſtone grauen by art, and mans deuice.</p>
                     <p n="19">19.<note place="margin">Habak. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> Woe vnto him that ſaith to the wood awake; to the dumbe ſtone ariſe, it ſhall teach; Behold it is laid ouer with gold, and ſiluer, and there is no <pb n="44" facs="tcp:565:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> breath at all in the middeſt of it.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note>3. Your eyes haue ſeene what the Lord did becauſe of <hi>Baal Peor;</hi> for all the men that followed <hi>Baal Peor</hi> the Lord thy God hath deſtroyed them from you.</p>
                     <p n="52">
                        <note place="margin">Numb. 33.</note>52. Yee ſhall driue out all the inhabitants of the land from before you, and deſtroy all their pictures, and deſtroy all their moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Images, and quite pluck downe all their high places.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 7.</note>5. Ye ſhall deſtroy their Altars, and breake downe their Images, and cut
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:565:38"/> downe their groues, and burne their grauen Images with fire.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">2 Cro. 34.</note> 
                        <hi>Ioſiah</hi> while he was yet young, began to ſeeke after the God of <hi>Dauid</hi> his father, and began to purge Iudah and Ieruſalem from the high places, and the groues, and the carued I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and the moulten I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And they brake downe the Altars of <hi>Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim</hi> in his preſence, and the Images that were on high aboue them be cut downe, and the groues, and the carued Images, and the moulten Images he brake
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:565:39"/> in peeces, and made duſt of them, and ſtrowed it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the graues of them that had ſacrificed vnto them.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. And hee burnt the bones of the Prieſts vpon their altars, and cleanſed Iudah and Ieruſalem.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">1. Sam. 7</note>3. If ye doe returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord with all your hearts; then put away the ſtrange Gods, and
<hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taroth</hi> from among you, and prepare your hearts vnto the Lord, and ſerue him onely.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael did put away
<hi>Baalim</hi> and <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> and ſerued the Lord onely.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:565:39"/>10.<note place="margin">Ier.
10.</note> The Lord is the true God, he is the liuing God, and an euerlaſting King; at his wrath the earth ſhall tremble, and the nations ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to abide his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="invocation" type="oracles">
                     <head>Inuocation.</head>
                     <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> WHoſoeuer ſhall call vpon the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaued.</p>
                     <p n="15">15.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> Call vpon mee in the day of trouble, I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">Zepha. 3</note> I will turne to the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:565:40"/> people a pure language, that they may all call vpon the name of the Lord, to ſerue him with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
                     <p n="59">
                        <note place="margin">Act. 7.</note>59 They ſtoned
<hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> calling vpon God, and ſaying, Lord Ieſus receiue my ſpirit.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note>2. When ye pray, ſay; <hi>Our father which art in heauen; hallowed bee thy name: Thy kingdome come: thy will be done, as in heauen ſo in earth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Giue vs day by day our dayly bread.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>And forgiue vs our ſinnes; for we alſo forgiue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that is indebted to <pb n="49" facs="tcp:565:40"/> vs. And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">Io. 16.</note> Whatſoeuer yee ſhall aſke the father in my name he will giue it you.</p>
                     <p n="28">28.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> Come vnto me all ye that labour, and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie laden, and I will giue you reſt.</p>
                     <p n="16">16.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> Let vs come boldly vnto the throne of grace, that we may obtaine mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and find grace to helpe in time of need.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note> Offer vnto GOD thankſgiuing, and pay thy vowes vnto the moſt high.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">18.</note> I will call vpon the Lord who is worthy to be <pb n="50" facs="tcp:565:41"/> praiſed, ſo ſhall I be ſaued from mine enemies.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. In my diſtreſſe I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Lord, and cryed vnto my God; Hee heard my voice out of his Temple, and my crie came before him, even into his eares.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">5.</note>3. My voice ſhalt thou heare in the morning, O Lord; in the morning will I direct my prayer vnto thee, and will looke vp.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">13.</note>3. Conſider, and heare me ô Lord my God; ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mine eyes, leaſt I ſleep the ſleepe of death.</p>
                     <p n="39">
                        <note place="margin">1. King. 8.</note>39. Heare thou in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thy dwelling place, &amp; <pb n="51" facs="tcp:565:41"/> forgiue, and doe, and giue to euery man according to his waies, whoſe heart thou knoweſt: for thou, euen thou onely knoweſt the hearts of all the children of men.</p>
                     <p n="16">16.<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.</note> Doubtleſſe thou art our father, though <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> be ignorant of vs, and Iſraell acknowledge vs not; thou ô Lord art our father, our redeemer, thy name is from euerlaſting.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Eccle. 9.</note> The liuing know that they ſhall die; but the dead know not any thing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue they any more a reward; for the memory of them is forgotten.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:565:42"/>6. Alſo their loue, and their hatred, and their enuy is now periſhed; neither haue they any more a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for euer in any thing that is done vnder the Sunne.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <note place="margin">Iob 14.</note>21. His ſonnes come to honour, and he knoweth it not; and they are brought low, but hee perceiueth it not of them.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 99.</note>6. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> among his Prieſts, and <hi>Samuel</hi> among them that call vpon his name, they called vpon the Lord, and he anſwered them.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He ſpake vnto them in the cloudy pillar: they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:565:42"/> kept his teſtimonies, and the ordinance that he gaue them.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> The ſame Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all is rich to all that call vpon him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="adoration" type="oracles">
                     <head>Adoration.</head>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> THe Lord is nigh vnto all them that call vpon him; to all that call vpon him in truth.</p>
                     <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">Io. 4.</note> The true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſhall worſhippe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſpirit and in truth: for the father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. God is a ſpirit, and they that worſhippe him,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:565:43"/> muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>17. The Sacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit, a broken and a contrite heart ô God thou wilt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe.</p>
                     <p n="20">
                        <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note>20. Ye are bought with a price, therefore glorifie God in your body, and in your ſpirit, which are Gods.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note>5. Yee alſo, as liuely ſtones, are built vp a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall houſe, an holy Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to offer vp ſpirituall Sacrifices acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note>3. We are the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion which worſhip God <pb n="55" facs="tcp:565:43"/> in the ſpirit, and reioyce in Chriſt Ieſus, and haue no confidence in the fleſh.</p>
                     <p n="20">20.<note place="margin">Ier. 6.</note> To what purpoſe commeth there to me In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe from Sheba? and the ſweete cane from a farre countrie? your burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings are not acceptable, nor your ſacrifices ſweete vnto me.</p>
                     <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">Amos. 5.</note> Take thou away from me the noiſe of thy ſongs, for I will not heare the melody of thy viols.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. But let iudgement run downe as waters, and righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtreame.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Micha. 6.</note> What doth the Lord
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:565:44"/> require of thee, but to do iuſtly, and to loue mercy, and to walke humbly with thy God?</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.</note>16. Waſh ye, make ye cleane, put away the euill of your doings from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine eyes, ceaſe to do euill;</p>
                     <p n="17">17. Learne to doe well, ſeeke iudgement, releeue the oppreſſed, iudge the fatherleſſe, pleade for the widdow.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note>4. Ye ſhall walke after the Lord your God, and feare him, and keepe his commandements, &amp; obey his voice, and ye ſhall ſerue him, and cleaue vnto him.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:565:44"/>12.<note place="margin">10.</note> What doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walke in all his waies, and to loue him, and to ſerue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule?</p>
                     <p n="13">13. To keepe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lord, and his ſtatutes, which I command thee this day for thy good.</p>
                     <p n="30">30.<note place="margin">Mar. 12.</note> Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy minde, and with all thy ſtrength: this is the firſt commandement.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:565:45"/>
                        <note place="margin">Ioſh.
22.</note>5. Take diligent heed to doe the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the law which
<hi>Moſes</hi> the ſeruant of the Lord charged you; to loue the Lord your God, and to walke in all his wayes, and to keepe his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and to cleaue vnto him, and to ſerue him with all your heart, and with all your ſoule.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">Col. 2.</note>18. Let no man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile you of your reward in a voluntary humilitie, and worſhipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, intruding into thoſe things which hee hath not ſeene, vainely puft vp by his fleſhly minde.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:565:45"/>8. When I had heard,<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note> and ſeene, I fell downe to worſhip before the feete of the Angel, which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me theſe things.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Then ſaith hee vnto me, ſee thou do it not; for I am thy fellow ſeruant, and of thy brethren the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and of them which keepe the ſayings of this booke; worſhip God.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">19.</note> And I fell at his feet to worſhip him, and he ſaid vnto me; ſee thou do it not; I am thy fellow ſeruant, and of thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that haue the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Ieſus; Worſhip God.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:565:46"/>2. The Lord is great in Zion, and he is high aboue all people.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Exalt yee the Lord our God, and worſhip at his footſtoole, for hee is holy.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.</note>14. Feare the Lord, and ſerue him in ſinceritie, and in truth, and put away the Gods which your fathers ſerued on the other ſide of the flood, and in Egipt, and ſerue ye the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.</note>13. Sanctifie the Lord of hoſts himſelfe, and let him be your feare, and let him be your dread.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">Reuel 14.</note>7. Worſhip him that made heauen, and earth, <pb n="61" facs="tcp:565:46"/> and the ſea, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of waters.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Luke 4.</note> Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy GOD, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="faith" type="oracles">
                     <head>Faith.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> FAith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for; the euidence of things not ſeene.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Hee that commeth to God, muſt beleeue that he is, and that hee is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of them that dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſeeke him.</p>
                     <p n="46">46.<note place="margin">Io. 12.</note> I am come a light into the world, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <pb n="62" facs="tcp:565:47"/> beleeueth on mee ſhould not abide in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                     <p n="36">
                        <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note>36. He that beleeueth on the ſonne, hath euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life; and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not the ſonne ſhall not ſee life: but the wrath of God ſhall abide on him.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <note place="margin">Galat. 3.</note>26. Ye are the children of God by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. The Scripture hath concluded all vnder ſinne, that the promiſe by faith of Ieſus Chriſt might bee giuen to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
                     <p n="43">
                        <note place="margin">Act. 10.</note>43. To him giue all the <pb n="63" facs="tcp:565:47"/> Prophets witneſſe, that through his name, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer belieueth in him, ſhall receiue remiſſion of ſins.</p>
                     <p n="22">22.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> Let vs draw neare with a true heart, in full aſſurance of faith.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. Let vs hold faſt the profeſſion of our faith without wauering, for hee is faithfull that promiſed.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. If thou ſhalt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> and ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in thine heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt bee ſaued.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. For with the heart man beleeueth vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: <pb n="64" facs="tcp:565:48"/> and with the mouth confeſſion is made vnto ſaluation.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note>9. They that be of faith are bleſſed, with faithfull <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note>9. The end of your faith, the ſaluation of your ſoules.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="repentence" type="oracles">
                     <head>Repentance.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.</note>1. O Iſrael returne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord thy God; for thou haſt fallen by thine iniquitie.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">Act. 3.</note>19. Repent yee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and bee conuerted, that your ſinnes may bee blotted out.</p>
                     <p n="23">
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:565:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>23.<note place="margin">Ezech.
18.</note> Haue I any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at all that the wicked ſhould die, ſaith the Lord God? and not that hee ſhould returne from his wayes and liue.</p>
                     <p n="30">30. Repent and turne your ſelues from all your tranſgreſſions, ſo iniquitie ſhall not be your
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. Caſt away from you all your tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whereby you haue tranſgreſſed; and make you a new heart, and a new ſpirit.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Turne ye, turne ye,<note place="margin">33.</note> from your euill waies, for why will ye die,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ô houſe of Iſrael?</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <pb n="66" facs="tcp:565:49"/>
                        <note place="margin">Iſa.
1.</note>18. Come now and let vs reaſon together, ſaith the Lord, though your ſinnes bee as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow; though they bee red like crimſon, they ſhall bee as wooll.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note>9. The Lord is long ſuffering to vs-ward, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.</note>7. Let the wicked forſake his way, and the vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man his thoughts, and let him returne vnto the Lord, and hee will haue mercy vpon him; and to our GOD, for hee will
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:565:49"/> abundantly pardon.</p>
                     <p n="40">40. Let vs ſearch,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> and trie our wayes and turne againe to the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. The Lord is good to them that waite for him, to the ſoule that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him.</p>
                     <p n="27">27.<note place="margin">Iob. 33.</note> If any ſay I haue ſinned, and peruerted that which was right, and it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited me not;</p>
                     <p n="28">28. He will deliuer his ſoule from going into the pit, and his life ſhall fee the light</p>
                     <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.</note> Let Iſraell hope in the Lord, for with the Lord there is mercie, and with him is plenteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:565:50"/>8. And hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme Iſraell from all his iniquities.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="confession" type="oracles">
                     <head>Confeſſion.</head>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 28.</note>13. HEe that couereth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper, but who ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, and forſaketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall haue mercy.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">Luke 15.</note>18. I will ariſe, and go to my father, and will ſay vnto him, father, I haue ſinned againſt heauen, and before thee,</p>
                     <p n="19">19. And am no more worthy to bee called thy ſonne.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="69" facs="tcp:565:50"/>5.<note place="margin">Pſal.
32.</note> I acknowledged my ſinne vnto thee, and mine iniquitie haue I not hid, I ſaid I will confeſſe my tranſgreſſions vnto the Lord, and thou forgaueſt the iniquitie of my ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> I prayed vnto the Lord my God, and made my confeſſion, and ſaid; O Lord the great and dreadfull God, keeping the couenant, and mercie to them that loue him, and to them that keepe his commandements;</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Wee haue ſinned and committed iniquitie, and haue done wickedly, and haue rebelled, euen <pb n="70" facs="tcp:565:51"/> by departing from thy precepts, and from thy iudgements.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">Dan 9.</note>6. Neither haue wee hearkened vnto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants the prophets, which ſpake in thy name to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, and to all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the land.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Nehem. 1</note>5. O Lord God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the great and terrible God, that keepeth coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and mercie for them that loue him, and obſerue his commandements;</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Let thine eare bee now attentiue, and thine eyes ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that thou mayſt heare the prayer of thy <pb n="71" facs="tcp:565:51"/> ſeruant which I pray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee now, day and night, for the children of Iſrael thy ſeruants; and confeſſe the ſinnes of the children of Iſrael, which wee haue ſinned againſt thee, both I, and my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe haue ſinned.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. We haue dealt very corruptly againſt thee, and haue not kept the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, nor the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, nor the Iudgements, which thou commandedſt thy ſeruant <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.</note> 
                        <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid vnto the Lord, I haue ſinned great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that I haue done; and now I beſeech thee O <pb n="72" facs="tcp:565:52"/> Lord, take away the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie of thy ſeruant, for I haue done fooliſhly.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Luke 18.</note>13. The publican ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding afarre off, would not lift vp ſo much as his eyes vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſmote vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his breſt, ſaying, God be merciful vnto me a ſinner.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn 1.</note>9. If wee confeſſe our ſinnes, hee is faithfull, and iuſt to forgiue vs our ſinnes, and to cleanſe vs from all vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note>11. As I liue, ſaith the Lord, euery knee ſhall bow to me, and euery tongue ſhall confeſſe to God.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. So then euery one of vs ſhall giue account
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:565:52"/> of himſelfe vnto God.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.</note> Lord be mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me heale my ſoule; for I haue ſinned againſt thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="faith and works" type="oracles">
                     <head>Faith and works.</head>
                     <p n="22">22.<note place="margin">Iames 1.</note> BE yee doers of the word, and not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers onely, deceiuing your owne ſelues.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. For if any be a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the word, and not a doer, he is like vnto a man beholding his naturall face in a glaſſe:</p>
                     <p n="24">24. For hee beholdeth himſelfe, and goeth his way, and ſtraight way for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth what manner of man he was.</p>
                     <p n="25">
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:565:53"/>
                        <note place="margin">Iam.
1.</note>25. But who ſo looketh into the perfect law of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, &amp; continueth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, he being not a forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearer, but a doer of the worke, this man ſhall be bleſſed in his deed.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. If any among you ſeeme to be religious, and bridle not his tongue, but deceiueth his owne heart; this mans religion is vaine.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. Pure religion and vndefiled before God and the father is this; to viſit the fatherleſſe, and the widdowes in their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to keepe himſelfe vnſpotted from the world.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note>13. Not the hearers of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:565:53"/> the law are iuſt before God, but the doers of the law ſhall be iuſtified.</p>
                     <p n="21">21.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> Not euery one that ſaith vnto me Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen; but hee that doth the will of my father which is in heauen.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Whoſoeuer heareth theſe ſayings of mine, and doth them, I will liken him vnto a wiſe man which built his houſe vpon a rock:</p>
                     <p n="25">25. And the raine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beate vpon that houſe, and it fell not; for it was
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:565:54"/> founded vpon a rocke.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note>26. And euery one that heareth theſe ſayings of mine, and doth them not; ſhall be likened vnto a fooliſh man which built his houſe vpon the ſand:</p>
                     <p n="27">27. And the raine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat vpon that houſe, and it fell; and great was the fall of that houſe.</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">5.</note>16. Let your light ſo ſhine before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they may ſee your good works and glorifie your father which is in heauen.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">5. Peter 1.</note>5. Adde to your faith vertue, &amp; to vertue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:565:54"/>6. And to knowledge temperance, and to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance patience, and to patience godlineſſe:</p>
                     <p n="7">7. And to godlineſſe brotherly kindneſſe, and to brotherly kindnes cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie:</p>
                     <p n="8">8. For if theſe things be in you, and abound, they make you that you ſhall neither be barren, nor vnfruitfull in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. But he that lacketh theſe things is blind &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee farre off, and hath forgotten that he was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from his old ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:565:55"/>
                        <note place="margin">2. Pet.
1.</note>10. Wherefore the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brethren, giue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to make your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and election ſure: for if ye do theſe things, yee ſhall neuer fall.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. For ſo an entrance ſhall bee miniſtred vnto you abundantly into the euerlaſting kingdome of our Lord and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note>8. This is a faithfull ſaying, and theſe things I will that thou affirme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, that they which haue beleeued in God might be carefull to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine good workes: theſe things are good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <pb n="79" facs="tcp:565:55"/> vnto men.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> What doth it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit my brethren, though a man ſay, he hath faith, and haue not works, can faith ſaue him?</p>
                     <p n="15">15. If a brother, or a ſiſter be naked, and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of dayly foode;</p>
                     <p n="16">16. And one of you ſay vnto them, depart in peace, bee you warmed, and filled; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding yee giue them not thoſe things which are needfull for the body; what doth it profit?</p>
                     <p n="17">17. Euen ſo faith, if it haue not works, is dead, being alone.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <pb n="80" facs="tcp:565:56"/>
                        <note place="margin">Iames
2.</note>21. Was not <hi>Abraham</hi> our father iuſtified by works when hee had offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſonne vpon the Altar?</p>
                     <p n="22">22. Seeſt thou how faith wrought with his works? and by works was faith made perfect.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. And the Scripture was fullfilled, which ſaith,
<hi>Abraham</hi> beleeued God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe; and he was called the friend of GOD.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Yee ſee then how that by workes a man is iuſtified, and not by faith onely.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:565:56"/>26. For as the body without the ſpirit is dead, ſo faith without works is dead alſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="justification" type="oracles">
                     <head>Iuſtification.</head>
                     <p n="19">19. NOw wee know,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note> that what things ſoeuer the law ſaith, it ſaith to them that are vnder the law; that euery mouth may bee ſtopped, and all the world may become guiltie before God.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. Therefore by the deeds of the law there ſhal no fleſh bee iuſtified in his ſight; for by the law is the knowledge of ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:565:57"/>
                        <note place="margin">Rom.
3.</note>21. But now the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the law is manifeſted, being witneſſed by the law, and the Prophets.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. Euen the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, of God, which is by faith of Ieſus Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, and vpon all them that beleeue; for there is no difference.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. For all haue ſinned, and come ſhort of the glory of God;</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Being iuſtified free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his grace, through the redemption that is in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="28">28, Therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that a man is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:565:57"/> by faith without the deeds of the law.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. Do wee then make voyde the law through faith? God forbid: yea we eſtabliſh the law.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 To him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. But to him that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not, but beleeueth on him that iuſtifieth the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly; his faith is counted for righteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. The promiſe that he ſhould be the heire of the world was not to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> or his ſeed thorough the law, but thorough the righteouſneſſe of faith.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:565:58"/>
                        <note place="margin">Rom.
4.</note>14. For if they which are of the law be heires, faith is made voyd and the promiſe made of none effect.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note>1. Being iuſtified by faith wee haue peace with God, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt:</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By whom alſo wee haue acceſſe by faith into his grace, wherin we ſtand, and reioyce in hope of the glory of God.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. As by the offence of one iudgement came vpon all men to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of one the free gift came vpon all men <pb n="85" facs="tcp:565:58"/> vnto iuſtification of life.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Titus 3.</note> Not by workes of righteouſneſſe which wee haue done, but according to his mercy hee ſaued vs by the waſhing of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and renewing of the holy Ghoſt:</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Which he ſhed on vs abundantly, through Ieſus Chriſt our ſauiour.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. That being iuſtified by his grace, we ſhould be made heires according to the hope of eternall life.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.</note> By grace are yee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued through faith, and that not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God:</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Not of workes, leaſt <pb n="86" facs="tcp:565:59"/> any man ſhould boaſt.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">Galat. 5.</note>4. Chriſt is become of none effect vnto you, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer of you are iuſtified by the law; yee are fallen from grace.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. For we through the ſpirit, waite for the hope of righteouſneſſe by faith.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. For in Ieſus Chriſt, neither circumciſion auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth any thing, nor vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but faith which worketh by loue.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 17.</note>10. When ye ſhall haue done all thoſe things, which are commanded you, ſay, wee are vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruants: wee haue done that which was our <pb n="87" facs="tcp:565:59"/> dutie to doe.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> I count all things but loſſe, for the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord; for whom I haue ſuffered the loſſe of all things, and doe count them but dung that I may winne Chriſt;</p>
                     <p n="9">9. And bee found in him, not hauing mine owne righteouſnes, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is of God by faith.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Bee not ſlothfull,<note place="margin">Heb.
6.</note> but followers of them who through faith and <pb n="88" facs="tcp:565:60"/> patience inherit the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note>2. This onely would I learne of you, receiued ye the ſpirit by the workes of the law, or by the hearing of faith?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Are yee ſo fooliſh, hauing begun in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, are yee now made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by the fleſh?</p>
                     <p n="11">11. That no man is iuſtified by the law in the ſight of God, it is euident; for the iuſt ſhall liue by faith.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. If the inheritance be of the law, it is no more of promiſe: but God gaue it to <hi>Abraham</hi> by promiſe.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <pb n="89" facs="tcp:565:60"/>21.<note place="margin">Gal.
3.</note> For if there had been a law giuen which could haue giuen life, verily righteouſnes ſhould haue beene by the law.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. But the Scripture hath concluded all vnder ſinne; that the promiſe by faith of Ieſus Chriſt might be giuen to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. But before faith came, we were kept vnder the Law, ſhut vp vnto the faith which ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be reuealed.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Wherefore the law was our Schoolemaſter, to bring vs vnto Chriſt, that we might bee iuſtified by <pb n="90" facs="tcp:565:61"/> faith.</p>
                     <p n="25">
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note>25. But after that faith is come, we are no longer vnder a Schoolemaſter.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. For yee are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="fasting" type="oracles">
                     <head>Faſting.</head>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note>16. WHen ye faſt, be not as the Hipocrites, of a ſad coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; for they disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure their faces that they may appeare vnto men to faſt: verily I ſay vnto you, they haue their reward.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. But thou when thou faſteſt, anoint thine head,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:565:61"/> and waſh thy face:</p>
                     <p n="18">18. That thou appeare not vnto men to faſt, but vnto thy father which is in ſecret, &amp; thy father which ſeeth in ſecret, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thee openly.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.</note> Is it ſuch a faſt that I haue choſen, a day for a man to afflict his ſoule? Is it to bowe downe his head as a bulruſh, and to ſpread ſackloth, and aſhes vnder him? wilt thou call this a faſt, and an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable day to the Lord?</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Is not this the faſt that I haue choſen? to looſe the bonds of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to vndoe the heauie <pb n="92" facs="tcp:565:62"/> burthens, and to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that ye breake euery yoke?</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Is it not to deale thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poore that are caſt out to thine houſe? when thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou couer him, and that thou hide not thy ſelfe from thine owne fleſh?</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Zechar. 7.</note>5. When ye faſted, and mourned in the fift and ſeauenth moneth, euen thoſe ſeuentie yeares, did ye at all faſt vnto me, euen to me.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Thus ſpeaketh the Lord of Hoſtes, ſaying,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:565:62"/> execute true iudgement, and ſhew mercie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion euerie man to his brother?</p>
                     <p n="10">10. And oppreſſe not the widdow, nor the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, the ſtranger, nor the poore, and let not any of you imagine euill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his brother in your heart.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> I ſet my face vnto the Lord God to ſeeke by prayer, and ſupplication, with faſting, and ſackcloth and aſhes.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Nehem. 1.</note> I ſate downe and wept, and mourned cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dayes, and faſted and prayed before the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:565:63"/> Lord of heauen.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">1. Sam. 7.</note>6. The Iſraelites faſted and ſaid, <hi>We haue ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="37">
                        <note place="margin">Luke. 2.</note>37. <hi>Anna</hi> was a widdow of about foureſcore and foure yeares, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted not from the Temple; but ſerued God with faſting, and prayers day and night.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <note place="margin">udg 20.</note>26. All the children of Iſrael, and all the people went vp, and came vnto the Houſe of God and wept, and ſate there before the Lord and faſted that day vntill euen, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red burnt offerings, and peace offerings before <pb n="95" facs="tcp:565:63"/> the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">Ioel. 2.</note> Turne ye euen to me ſaith the Lord, with all your heart, and with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and with weeping, and with mourning.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. And rent your hearts and not your garments, and turne vnto the Lord your God, for he is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and mercifull, ſlow to anger, and of great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and repenteth him of the euill.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Blow the trumpet in Zion, ſanctifie a faſt, call a ſolemme aſſembly:</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Gather the people; ſanctifie the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; aſſemble the Elders; <pb n="96" facs="tcp:565:64"/> gather the children, and thoſe that ſuck the breaſts; let the bridegrome goe forth of his chamber, and the bride out of her clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <note place="margin">Ioel 2.</note>17. Let the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord weepe between the Porch and the Alter, and let them ſay, <hi>Spare thy people O Lord,</hi> and giue not thine heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to reproch; that the heathen ſhould rule ouer them.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Ionah 3.</note>5. The people of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neueh beleeued God, and proclaimed a faſt, and put on ſackloth, from the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of them, to the leaſt of <pb n="97" facs="tcp:565:64"/> them.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. And the king of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neueh aroſe from his throne, and hee layde his robe from him, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him with ſackloth, and ſate in aſhes.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. And he cauſed it to bee proclaimed, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed through Nineueh (by the decree of the king and his nobles) ſaying, let neither man nor beaſt, heard nor flocke taſte any thing; let them not feede, nor drinke water.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. But let man, and beaſt be couered with ſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and cry mightily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; yea let them turne <pb n="98" facs="tcp:565:65"/> euery one from his euill way, and from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that is in their hands.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">Ionah 3.</note>9. Who can tell if God will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ne, and repent, and turne away from his fierce anger, that we periſh not?</p>
                     <p n="10">10. And God ſaw their workes, that they turned from their euill way: and God repented of the euill that hee had ſaid, that hee would doe vnto them, and he did it not.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="food" type="oracles">
                     <head>Meates.</head>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">Col. 2.</note>16. LEt no man iudge you in meate or in drinke;</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note>17. For the kingdome
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:565:65"/> of God is not meate, and drink, but righteouſneſſe, and peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> Meate commendeth vs not to God, for neither if we eate, are wee the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; neither if we eate not, are we the worſe.</p>
                     <p n="25">25.<note place="margin">10.</note> Whatſoeuer is ſold in the ſhambles, that eate, making no queſtion for conſcience ſake: for the earth is the Lords, and the fullneſſe thereof.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> There is nothing vncleane of it ſelfe, but to him that eſteemeth any thing to bee vncleane, to him it is vncleane.</p>
                     <p n="15">
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:565:66"/>
                        <note place="margin">Tit.
1.</note>15. Vnto the pure all things are pure, but vnto them that are defiled, and vnbeleeuing, is nothing pure, but euen their mind, and conſcience is defiled.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note>11. Not that which goeth into the mouth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth a man, but that which commeth out of the mouth, this defileth a man.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. Thoſe things which proceede out of the mouth, come forth from the heart, and they defile the man.</p>
                     <p n="15">
                        <note place="margin">Mar. 7.</note>15. There is nothing from without a man that entring into him can defile <pb n="101" facs="tcp:565:66"/> him; but the things which come out of him, thoſe are they that defile the man.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. For from within out of the heart of men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede euill thoughts, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, fornications, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. Thefts, coueteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wickedneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, laſciuiouſneſſe, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill eye, blaſphemie, pride, fooliſhneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. All theſe euill things come from within, and defile the man.</p>
                     <p n="31">31.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> Whether ye eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer yee do, doe all to the glorie of God.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="102" facs="tcp:565:67"/>
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim.
4.</note>4. For euerie creature of God is good, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be refuſed, if it be receiued with thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. For it is ſanctified by the Word of God and prayer.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note>9. But take heede leaſt by any meanes this libertie of yours become a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke to them that are weake.</p>
                     <p n="15">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note>15. If thy brother bee grieued with thy meate, now walkeſt thou not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably; deſtroy not him with thy meate, for whom Chriſt died.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. All things indeede <pb n="103" facs="tcp:565:67"/> are pure, but it is euill for that man who eateth with offence.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. It is neither good to eate fleſh, nor to drinke wine, nor any thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thy brother ſtumbleth, or is offended, or is made weake.</p>
                     <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> If meate make my brother offend, I will eate no fleſh while the world ſtandeth, leſt I make my brother to offend.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> One beleeueth that he may eate all things, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, who is weake, eateth herbes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Let not him that eateth deſpiſe him that
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:565:68"/> eateth not; and let not him which eateth not, iudge him that eateth; for God hath receiued him.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note>6. Hee that eateth, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the Lord, for hee giueth God thankes: and hee that eateth not, to the Lord hee eateth not, and giueth God thanks.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. Hee that doubteth is damned if hee eate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee eateth not of faith: for whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. Let vs therefore follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one may edifie another.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="love" type="oracles">
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:565:68"/>
                     <head>Loue and Charitie.</head>
                     <p n="7">7. BEloued,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note> let vs loue one another, for loue is of God; and euery one that loueth, is borne of God, and knoweth God.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Hee that loueth not, knoweth not God; for God is loue.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. If we loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God dwelleth in vs, and his loue is perfect in vs.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. God is loue, and he that dwelleth in loue, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">2.</note> He that loueth his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:565:69"/> brother abideth in the light, and there is no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſtumbling in him.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. But hee that hateth his brother is in darkneſſe,<note place="margin">1. Iohh 4.</note> and walketh in darkeneſſe, and knoweth not whether hee goeth, becauſe that darkneſſe hath blinded his eyes.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. If a man ſay, I loue GOD, and hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee is a lier: for hee that loueth not his brother whom he hath ſeene, how can he loue God whom he hath not ſeene?</p>
                     <p n="21">21. And this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement haue wee from him, that hee that loueth <pb n="107" facs="tcp:565:69"/> GOD, loue his brother alſo.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> Loue worketh no ill to his neighbour, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore loue is the fullfilling of the law.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> For all the law is fullfilled in one word, euen in this, thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. But if yee bite, and deuoure one another, take heed ye be not conſumed one of another.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note> Yee your ſelues are taught of God to loue one another.</p>
                     <p n="22">22.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> See that ye loue one another with a pure heart feruently.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="108" facs="tcp:565:70"/>
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim.
1.</note>5. The end of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is charitie out of a pure heart, and of a good conſcience, and of faith vnfained.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.</note>18, Let vs not loue in word, neither in tongue, but in deed, and in truth.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 15.</note>7. Thou ſhalt not har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thy heart, nor ſhut thine hand from thy poore brother.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. But thou ſhalt open thy hand wide vnto him, and ſhalt ſurely lend him ſufficient for his neede in that which hee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Thou ſhalt ſurely giue him, and thine heart
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:565:70"/> ſhall not be grieued, when thou giueſt vnto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that for this thing, the Lord thy GOD ſhall bleſſe thee in all thy works, and in all that thou putteſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hine hand vnto.</p>
                     <p n="27">27 He that giueth vnto the poore ſhall not lacke;<note place="margin">Pro. 28.</note> but he that hideth his eyes, ſhall haue many a curſe.</p>
                     <p n="17">17.<note place="margin">19.</note> He that hath pittie vpon the poore lendeth vnto the Lord; and that which he hath giuen, will he pay him againe.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.</note> Bleſſed is he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth the poore, &amp; nee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, the Lord will deliuer him in time of trouble.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <pb n="110" facs="tcp:565:71"/>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 12</note>8. He that giueth, let him do it with ſimplicitie; he that ſheweth mercie with cheerefulneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.</note>17. Who ſo hath this worlds good, and ſeeth his brother hath neede, and ſhutteth vp his bowells of compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him?</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">1. Peter 4.</note>8. Aboue all things haue feruent charitie among your ſelues; for charitie ſhall couer the multitude of ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.</note>14. Let all your things be done with charitie.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 3.</note>12. And the Lord make you to increaſe and <pb n="111" facs="tcp:565:71"/> to abound in loue one towards another, and towards all men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="prayer" type="oracles">
                     <head>Prayer.</head>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> I Will that men pray euery where, lifting vp holy hands without wrath, and doubting.</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.</note> Praying alwayes with all prayer, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in the ſpirit.</p>
                     <p n="20">20.<note place="margin">Iude</note> Build vp your ſelues in your moſt holy faith praying in the holy Ghoſt.</p>
                     <p n="24">24.<note place="margin">Mark 11.</note> What things ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yee deſire when yee pray; beleeue that ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:565:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> them, and yee ſhall haue them.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. And when ye ſtand praying, forgiue if ye haue ought againſt any, that your father alſo which is in heauen may forgiue you your treſpaſſes.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. But if you do not forgiue, neither will your father which is in heauen forgiue you your treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>5. When thou prayeſt, thou ſhalt not bee as the Hipocrites are; for they loue to ſtand praying in Synagogues, and in the corners of the ſtreete, that they may be ſeene of men: <pb n="113" facs="tcp:565:72"/> verily I ſay vnto you, they haue their reward.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. But thou when thou prayeſt, enter into thy clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, and when thou haſt ſhut thy doore, pray to thy father which is in ſecret, and thy father which ſeeth in ſecret, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thee openly.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. When you pray, vſe not vaine repetitions as the heathen doe, for they thinke that they ſhall bee heard for their much ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
                     <p n="41">41.<note place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> Let vs lift vp our heart with our hands vnto God in the heauens.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> If I pray in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne <pb n="114" facs="tcp:565:73"/> tongue, my ſpirit prayeth, but mine vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is vnfruitfull.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. I will pray with the ſpirit, and will pray with vnderſtanding alſo.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. In the Church I had rather ſpeake fiue words with my vnderſtanding, that by my voice I might teach others alſo, then ten thouſand words in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. For if the trumpet giue an vncertaine ſound, who ſhall prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the battaile.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. So likewiſe you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept yee vtter by the tongue words eaſie to bee <pb n="115" facs="tcp:565:73"/> vnderſtood, how ſhall it bee knowne what is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? for ye ſpeake into the ayre.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Continue in prayer,<note place="margin">Col. 4.</note> and watch in the ſame with thankſegiuing.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> 
                        <hi>Daniel</hi> kneeled vpon his knees three times 1 day and prayed, and gaue thankes before his God.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. Euening,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.</note> and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and at noone will I pray, and cry aloude; and he ſhall heare my voice.</p>
                     <p n="16">16.<note place="margin">Iames 5.</note> Pray one for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that ye may be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; the effectuall feruent prayer of a righteous man availeth much.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <pb n="116" facs="tcp:565:74"/>13. Is any among you afflicted? let him pray.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="mediator" type="oracles">
                     <head>One Mediator.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.</note>1. IF any man ſinne, we haue an aduocate with the father IESVS CHRIST the righteous.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note>5. There is one God, and one Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and men, the man Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                     <p n="34">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note>34. Chriſt is euen at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for vs.</p>
                     <p n="25">
                        <note place="margin">Hebr. 7.</note>25. He is able alſo to ſaue them for euermore that come vnto God by <pb n="117" facs="tcp:565:74"/> him; ſeeing he euer liueth to make interceſſion for them.</p>
                     <p n="24">24.<note place="margin">9.</note> Chriſt is not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the holy places made with hands, which are the figures of the true
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, but into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it ſelfe, now to apeare in the preſence of God for vs.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. I am the way,<note place="margin">Iohn 14.</note> the truth, and the life, no man commeth vnto the father but by me.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">10.</note> He that entreth not in by the doore into the ſheepfold, but climeth vp ſome other way, the ſame is a thiefe, and a robber.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <pb n="118" facs="tcp:565:75"/>9. I am the doore, by me if any man enter in, he ſhall be ſaued.</p>
                     <p n="28">
                        <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note>28. Come vnto me all ye that labour and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie laden, and I will giue you reſt.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">28.</note>18. all power is giuen vnto me in heauen and in earth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="propitiation" type="oracles">
                     <head>Our Propitiation, Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and Satisfaction.</head>
                     <p n="25">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 3.</note>25. GOd hath ſet forth Chriſt Ieſus to be a propitiation through faith in his blood, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his righteouſneſſe for the remiſſion of ſinnes that are paſt, through the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance <pb n="119" facs="tcp:565:75"/> of God.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.</note> And he is the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our ſinnes, and not for ours onely, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the ſinnes of the whole world.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> Hee gaue himſelfe a ranſome for all to be teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in due time.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Iſay. 53.</note> Surely he hath borne our griefes, and carried our ſorrowes.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Hee was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, hee was bruiſed for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him, and with his ſtripes are we healed.</p>
                     <p n="25">25.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> Hee was deliuered
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:565:76"/> for our offences and was raiſed againe for our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</p>
                     <p n="24">
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note>24. His owne ſelfe bare our ſinnes in his owne body on the tree, that wee being dead to ſinne, ſhould liue vnto righteouſneſſe; by whoſe ſtripes we were healed.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. For yee were as ſheepe going aſtray, but now are returned to the ſheapheard and Biſhop of your ſoules.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note>11. We alſo ioy in God thorough our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by whom we haue now receiued the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <pb n="121" facs="tcp:565:76"/>10. When we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, wee were reconciled vnto God, by the death of his ſonne.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">Heb. 5.</note> Being made perfect hee became the author of eternall ſaluation vnto all that obey him.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">1.</note> When he had by himſelfe purged our ſins, he ſate downe on the right hand of the maieſtie on high.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">9.</note> By his owne blood he entred in once into the holy place, hauing obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eternall redemption for vs.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. Once in the end of the world hath hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:565:77"/> to put away ſinne by the Sacrifice of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="28">
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note>28. Chriſt was offered once, to beare the ſinnes of many.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note>18. All things are of God who hath reconciled vs vnto himſelfe by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 4.</note>10. Herein is loue, not that wee loued God, but that he loued vs, and ſent his Sonne to be the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for our ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="36">
                        <note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note>36. If the Sonne ſhall make you free, ye ſhall be free indeede.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn 1.</note>7. If wee walke in the light, as he is in the light, <pb n="123" facs="tcp:565:77"/> wee haue fellowſhip one with another, and the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt clenſeth vs from all ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. If wee confeſſe our ſinnes, he is faithfull, and iuſt to forgiue vs our ſinnes, and to clenſe vs from all vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> Ye were not redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with corruptible things, as ſiluer and gold, from your vaine conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation receiued by tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from your fathers.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. But with the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud of Chriſt as of a lambe without blemiſh, and without ſpot.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> For by one offering <pb n="124" facs="tcp:565:78"/> he hath perfected for euer them that are ſanctified.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note>7. Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, and whoſe ſinnes are couered.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Bleſſed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="sins" type="oracles">
                     <head>Sinnes.</head>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 20.</note>9. WHo can ſay, I haue made my heart cleane? I am pure from my ſinne?</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.</note>4. Sinne is the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note>10. As many as are of the workes of the Law, are <pb n="125" facs="tcp:565:78"/> vnder the curſe: for it is written, curſed is euery one that continueth not in all things which are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of the Law to doe them.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Ia. 2.</note> Whoſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, he is guiltie of all.</p>
                     <p n="36">36.<note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> Euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue an account therof in the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p n="22">22.<note place="margin">5.</note> Whoſoeuer is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie with his brother, without a cauſe ſhall bee in danger of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and whoſoeuer ſhall <pb n="126" facs="tcp:565:79"/> ſay vnto his brother, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha, ſhall bee in danger of the Councell: But who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhal ſay thou foole, ſhall bee in danger of hell fire.</p>
                     <p n="23">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note>23. The wages of ſinne is death.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">7.</note>11. Sinne taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deceiued me, and by it ſlew me.</p>
                     <p n="20">
                        <note place="margin">Ezech. 18.</note>20. The ſoule that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſhall die.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note>12. As by one man ſin entred into the world, and death by ſinne: ſo death paſſed vpon all men, for that all haue ſinned.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note>5. For this yee know,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:565:79"/> that no whoremonger, nor vncleane perſon, nor couetous man who is an Idolater, hath any inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the kingdome of Chriſt, and of God.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Let no man deceiue you with vaine words; for becauſe of theſe things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the wrath of God vpon the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
                     <p n="30">30.<note place="margin">Ezech. 18</note> I will iudge you ô houſe of Iſrael, euery one according to his wayes ſaith the Lord God: repent and turne your ſelues from all your tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo iniquitie ſhall not be your ruine.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <pb n="128" facs="tcp:565:80"/>
                        <note place="margin">Gen.
19</note>26. <hi>Lots</hi> wife looked backe from behind him, &amp; ſhe became a pillar of ſalt.</p>
                     <p n="36">
                        <note place="margin">Num. 15.</note>36. All the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion brought the man that gathered ſtickes vpon the Sabbath day without the campe, and ſtoned him with ſtones, and he died, as the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Leuit. 24.</note>13. The Lord ſpake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaying;</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Bring foorth him that hath curſed, without the campe, and let all that heard him, lay their hands vpon his head, and let all the Congregation ſtone him.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="129" facs="tcp:565:80"/>6.<note place="margin">2. Sam.
6.</note> 
                        <hi>Vzzah</hi> put forth his hand to the Arke of God, and tooke hold of it, for the oxen ſhooke it.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. And the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt
<hi>Vzzah,</hi> and God ſmote him there for his error, and there he died by the Arke of God.</p>
                     <p n="19">19.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.</note> And hee ſmote the men of Beth-ſhemeſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had looked into the Arke of the Lord, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee ſmote of the people threeſcore thouſand, and threeſcore, and ten men.</p>
                     <p n="30">30.<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> Caſt ye the vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruant into vtter darkeneſſe, there ſhall bee
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:565:81"/> weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Iam. 3.</note>2. In many things wee offend all.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 1.</note>7. And the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt cleanſeth vs from all ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="will" type="oracles">
                     <head>Will.</head>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note>5. GOd ſaw that the wickednes of man was great in the earth, and that euery imagination of the thoughts of his heart was onely euill continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <note place="margin">8.</note>21. The imagination of mans heart is euill from his youth.</p>
                     <p n="23">
                        <pb n="131" facs="tcp:565:81"/>23.<note place="margin">Ier.
10.</note> O Lord I know that the way of man is not in himſelfe, it is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps.</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">31.</note> Thou haſt chaſtiſed me, and I was chaſtiſed as a bullocke vnaccuſtomed to the yoake; turne thou me, and I ſhall be turned, thou art the Lord my God.</p>
                     <p n="24">24.<note place="margin">Pro. 20.</note> Mans goings are of the Lord; how can a man then vnderſtand his owne way.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">16.</note> The preparations of the heart of man, and the anſwer of the tongue, is from the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.</note> I am the vine ye are <pb n="132" facs="tcp:565:82"/> the branches; he that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in me, and I in him, the ſame bringeth foorth much fruit, for without me ye can do nothing.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.</note>8. I will inſtruct thee and teach thee in the way that thou ſhalt goe: I will guide thee with mine eye.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">Hoſea 13.</note>9. O Iſrael thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed thy ſelfe, but in me is thine helpe.</p>
                     <p n="44">
                        <note place="margin">Iohn 6.</note>44. No man can come to mee, except the father which hath ſent me, draw him.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.</note>5. We are not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of our ſelues to thinke any thing as of our ſelues: for our ſufficiency is of <pb n="133" facs="tcp:565:82"/> God.</p>
                     <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">Philip. 2.</note> It is God which worketh in you both to will, and to doe of his good pleaſure.</p>
                     <p n="17">17.<note place="margin">Iames 1.</note> Euery good gift, and euery perfect gift, is from aboue, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth downe from the father of lights; with whom is no variableneſſe, neither ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of turning.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. Of his owne will begate hee vs, with the word of truth, that wee ſhould bee a kinde of firſt fruits of his creatures.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Ye ought to ſay,<note place="margin">Iames
4.</note> if the Lord will, we ſhall liue, and doe this, or that.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <pb n="134" facs="tcp:565:83"/>
                        <note place="margin">Acts
18:</note>21. I will returne againe vnto you, if God will.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note>19. I will come vnto you ſhortly if the Lord will.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note>3. This will wee doe if God permit.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <note place="margin">Ezech. 36.</note>26. A new heart will I giue you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you, and I will take away the ſtony heart out of your fleſh, and I will giue you an heart of fleſh.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. And I will put my ſpirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my ſtatutes, and ye ſhall keepe my iudgements, and doe them.</p>
                     <p n="45">
                        <pb n="135" facs="tcp:565:83"/>45.<note place="margin">Luke
24.</note> Then opened hee their vnderſtanding, that they might vnderſtand the Scriptures.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> As many as recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued him, to them gaue he power to become the ſonnes of God, euen to them that beleeue on his name.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Which were borne not of blood nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man but of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="hypocrisy" type="oracles">
                     <head>Hipocriſie.</head>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Iames 4.</note> CLeanſe your hands ye ſinners; and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your hearts ye double <pb n="136" facs="tcp:565:84"/> minded.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Luke 12.</note>1. Beware ye of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the Phariſes which is hypocriſie.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 30.</note>12. There is a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that are pure in their owne eyes, and yet is not waſhed from their filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Iob 36.</note>13. The hypocrites in heart heape vp wrath.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Iſay. 58</note>2. They ſeeke mee dayly, and delight to know my wayes, as a nation that did righteouſneſſe, and forſook not the ordinance of their God, they aske of mee the ordinances of Iuſtice, they take delight in aproaching to God.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <pb n="137" facs="tcp:565:84"/>5.<note place="margin">Mat.
23.</note> But all their workes they doe, for to be ſeene of men.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. Woe vnto you Scribes and Phariſes, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites; for yee pay tythe of mynt and anniſe, and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myne, and haue omitted the weightier matters of the law, iudgement, mercy, and faith: theſe ought yee to haue done, and not to leaue the other vndone.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. Ye are like to whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſepulchers, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede appeare beautifull outward, but are within full of dead mens bones, and of vncleaneneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. Euen ſo yee alſo <pb n="138" facs="tcp:565:85"/> outwardly appeare righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto men, but within ye are full of hypocriſie and iniquitie.</p>
                     <p n="39">
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note>39. Yee Phariſees doe make cleane the outſide of the cup and platter, but your inward part is full of rauening, and wickedneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note>26. Cleanſe firſt that which is within the cup, and platter, that the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of them may bee cleane alſo.</p>
                     <p n="40">
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note>40. Ye fooles, did not he which made that which is without, make that which is within alſo?</p>
                     <p n="41">41. Rather giue almes <pb n="139" facs="tcp:565:85"/> of ſuch things as you haue; &amp; behold all things are cleane vnto you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="riches" type="oracles">
                     <head>Riches.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6.</note> THere is an euill which I haue ſeene vnder the Sunne, and it is common among men.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. A man to whom God hath giuen riches, wealth, and honour, ſo that hee wanteth nothing for his ſoule of all that hee deſireth, yet God giueth him not power to eate thereof, but a ſtranger eateth it: this is vanitie, <pb n="140" facs="tcp:565:86"/> and it is an euill diſeaſe.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note>17. Charge them that bee rich in this world, that they bee not high minded, nor truſt in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine riches, but in the liuing God, who giueth vs richly all things to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. That they doe good, that they bee rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. Laying vp in ſtore for themſelues a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternall life.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Iames 5.</note>1. Goe to now ye rich
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:565:86"/> men, weepe and howle for your miſeries that ſhal come vpon you.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Your riches are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and your garments moth-eaten.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Your gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is cankred, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe againſt you, and ſhall eate your fleſh as it were fire; yee haue heaped vp trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure together for the laſt dayes.</p>
                     <p n="24">24 Woe vnto you that are rich,<note place="margin">Luke
6.</note> for ye haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your conſolation.</p>
                     <p n="19">19.<note place="margin">Mar. 4.</note> The cares of this world, and the deceitfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of riches, and the <pb n="142" facs="tcp:565:87"/> luſts of other things en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in, choake the word, and it becommeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note>13. Yee cannot ſerue God and Mammon.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim 6.</note>6. Godlineſſe with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is great gaine.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 62.</note>10. If riches increaſe, ſet not your heart vpon them.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.</note>7. For we brought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into this world, and it is certaine we can carrie nothing out.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. And hauing foode and raiment, let vs be ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with content.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. But they that will be rich fall into temptation,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:565:87"/> and a ſnare, and into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fooliſh, and hurtfull luſts which drowne men in deſtruction, and perdition.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. For the loue of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is the roote of all euill; which while ſome coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after, they haue erred from the faith, and pierced themſelues thorough with many ſorrowes.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. Thou foole, this night thy ſoule ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of thee;<note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> then whoſe ſhall thoſe things bee which thou haſt prouided.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. So is he that layeth vp treaſure for himſelfe, and is not rich towards God.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <pb n="144" facs="tcp:565:88"/>
                        <note place="margin">Pro.
18.</note>11. The rich mans wealth is his ſtrong citie; and as an high wall in his owne conceit.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">11.</note>4. Riches profit not in the day of wrath; but righteouſneſſe deliuereth from death.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <note place="margin">Zepha. 1.</note>18. Neither their ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, nor their gold ſhall be able to deliuer them in the day of the Lords wrath.</p>
                     <p n="15">
                        <note place="margin">Luke 12.</note>15. A mans life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of things which hee poſſeſſeth.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. Rather ſeeke ye the kingdome of God, and all theſe things ſhall bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="patience" type="oracles">
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:565:88"/>
                     <head>Patience.</head>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.</note> BE patient towards all men.</p>
                     <p n="15">15, See that none ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der euill for euill vnto any man, but euer follow that which is good, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelues, and to all men.</p>
                     <p n="19">19.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> Auenge not your ſelues, but rather giue place vnto wrath; for it is written, vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is mine, I will repay, ſaith the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Iames 1.</note> The trying of your faith worketh patience.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. But let patience haue <pb n="146" facs="tcp:565:89"/> her perfect worke, that ye may be perfect, and entire, wanting nothing.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note>3. Tribulations worke patience.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And patience expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and experience hope.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 21.</note>19. In your patience poſſeſſe ye your ſelues.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note>5. Let your moderation be knowne vnto all men.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note>19. Let euery man bee ſwift to heare, ſlow to ſpeake, ſlow to wrath.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. For the wrath of man worketh not the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God.</p>
                     <p n="32">
                        <note place="margin">Pro. 16.</note>32. Hee that is ſlow to anger, is better then the <pb n="147" facs="tcp:565:89"/> mightie, and hee that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his ſpirit, then he that taketh a citie.</p>
                     <p n="29">29.<note place="margin">14.</note> Hee that is ſlow to wrath, is of great vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; but hee that is haſtie of ſpirit, exalteth folly.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Wrath is cruell,<note place="margin">27.</note> and anger is outragious.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.</note> Bee not haſtie in thy ſpirit to bee angry, for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger reſteth in the boſome of fooles.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Iam. 5.</note> Bee patient vnto the comming of the Lord; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the huſbandman wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, vntill he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:565:90"/> the early, and later raine.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Bee yee alſo patient, ſtabliſh your hearts: for the comming of the Lord draweth nigh.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Take the Prophets, who haue ſpoken in the name of the Lord, for an example of ſuffering affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and of patience.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Behold wee count them happy which indure: yee haue heard of the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>Iob,</hi> and haue ſeene the end of the Lord; that the Lord is pittifull, and of tender mercy.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note>10. The GOD of all grace, who hath called vs <pb n="149" facs="tcp:565:90" rendition="simple:additions"/> into his eternall glorie by Chriſt Ieſus, after that yee haue ſuffered a while, make perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. To him bee glory and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="humiliation" type="oracles">
                     <head>Humilitie.</head>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> HVmble your ſelues vnder the mightie hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Yea, all of you bee ſubiect one to another, and be clothed with humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: for God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:565:91"/> the humble.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>o. 16.</note>19. Better it is to be of an humble ſpirit with the lowly, then to deuide the ſpoile with the proud.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">11.</note>2. When pride com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, then commeth ſhame, but with the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is wiſedome.</p>
                     <p n="29">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note>29. Learne of me, for I am lowly in heart.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uk. 14.</note>11. Whoſoeuer exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe ſhall be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and he that humbleth himſelfe ſhall bee exalted.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pheſ: 4.</note>1. Walke worthy of the vocation wherein yee are called.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. With all lowlineſſe, and meekeneſſe, with long <pb n="151" facs="tcp:565:91"/> ſuffering, forbearing one another in loue.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Phil 2.</note> Let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vaine-glory, but in lowlineſſe of minde let each eſteeme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Let this minde be in you which was alſo in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Who made himſelfe of no reputation, and tooke vpon him the forme of a ſeruant, and was made in the likeneſſe of men.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Hee humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and became obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnto death, euen the death of the croſſe.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <pb n="152" facs="tcp:565:92"/>
                        <note place="margin">Phil.
2.</note>9. Wherefore God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath highly exalted him, and giuen him a name which is aboue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. That at the name of Ieſus euery knee ſhould bow, of things in heauen, and things in earth, and things vnder the earth.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. And that euery tongue ſhould confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt is Lord, to the glory of God the father.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 138.</note>6. Though the Lord be high, yet hee hath reſpect vnto the lowly, but the proude he knoweth afarre off.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <pb n="153" facs="tcp:565:92"/>9.<note place="margin">25.</note> The meeke will he guide in iudgement, and the meeke will hee teach his way.</p>
                     <p n="34">34.<note place="margin">Pro. 3.</note> Surely he ſcorneth the ſcorners: but he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth grace vnto the lowly.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.</note> The Lord lifteth vp the meeke: hee caſteth the vngodly downe to the ground.</p>
                     <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> Two men went vp into the Temple to pray, the one a Phariſee, and the other a Publican.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. The Phariſe ſtood &amp; prayed thus with himſelfe; God, I thank thee that I am not as other men are, exortioners, vniuſt, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, <pb n="154" facs="tcp:565:93"/> and euen as this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">Luke 18.</note>12. I faſt twiſe in the weeke, I giue tithes of all that I poſſeſſe.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. And the Publican ſtanding a farre off, would not lift vp ſo much as his eyes vnto heauen; but ſmote vpon his breſt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. I tell you, this man went downe to his houſe iuſtified, rather then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for euery one that exalteth himſelfe ſhall be abaſed: and he that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himſelf ſhall be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Eucharist" type="oracles">
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:565:93"/>
                     <head>The holy Euchariſt.</head>
                     <p n="26">26. IEſus tooke bread,<note place="margin">Mat.
26.</note> and bleſſed it, and brake it, and gaue it to the Diſciples, and ſaid, take, eate, this is my body.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. And he tooke the cup, and gaue thankes, and gaue it to them, ſaying; drinke ye all of it.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. For this is my blood of the new Teſtament, which is ſhed for many for the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. Ieſus tooke bread,<note place="margin">Mark.
14.</note> and bleſſed, and brake it, &amp; gaue to them, and ſaid; take, eate, this is my bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p n="23">
                        <pb n="156" facs="tcp:565:94"/>23. And hee tooke the cup, and when hee had giuen thankes, hee gaue it to them, and they all dranke of it.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. And hee ſaid vnto them, this is my blood of the new Teſtament, which is ſhed for many.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">Luke 22.</note>19. Hee tooke bread, and gaue thankes, and brake it, and gaue vnto them, ſaying, this is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is giuen for you; this doe in remembrance of me.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. Likewiſe alſo the cup after ſupper, ſaying; this cup is the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my blood, which <pb n="157" facs="tcp:565:94"/> is ſhed for you.</p>
                     <p n="16">16.<note place="margin">1. Co. 10.</note> The cup of bleſſing which wee bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the blood of CHRIST? The bread which we breake, is it not the Communion of the body of Chriſt?</p>
                     <p n="17">17. For we being many, are one bread, and one body; for we are all parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of that one bread.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. The Lord Ieſus the ſame night in which hee was betraied, tooke bread;</p>
                     <p n="24">24. And when hee had giuen thankes, he brake it, and ſaid; take, eate, this is my body which is broken for you; this doe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance <pb n="158" facs="tcp:565:95"/> of mee.</p>
                     <p n="25">
                        <note place="margin">Cor. 11.</note>25. After the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner alſo hee tooke the cup when he had ſupped, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; this cup is the new Teſtament in my blood: this doe, as oft as ye drinke it, in remembrance of me.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. For as often as yee eate this bread, and drinke this cup, yee doe ſhew the Lords death till he come.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. Wherefore who ſoeuer ſhall eate this bread, and drinke this cup of the Lord vnworthily, ſhall bee guiltie of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud of the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. But let a man exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe, and ſo let
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:565:95"/> him eate of that bread, and drinke of that cup.</p>
                     <p n="29">29. For he that eateth, and drinketh vnworthily, eateth and drinketh dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to himſelfe, not diſcerning the Lords bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Cor. 10.</note> Our fathers did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke; for they dranke of that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall rocke that followed them, and that rocke was Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="35">35. Ieſus ſaid,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6</note> I am the bread of life, he that com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth to mee, ſhall neuer
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:565:96"/> hunger, and he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth on me, ſhall neuer thirſt.</p>
                     <p n="51">51. I am the liuing bread which came downe from heauen: If any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for euer: and the bread that I will giue is my fleſh, which I will giue for the life of the world.</p>
                     <p n="56">56. He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me and I in him.</p>
                     <p n="58">58. Not as your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did eate Manna, and are dead; he that eateth of this bread, ſhall liue for euer.</p>
                     <p n="63">
                        <pb n="161" facs="tcp:565:96"/>63.<note place="margin">Iohn
6.</note> It is the ſpirit that quickeneth, the fleſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing: the words that I ſpeake vnto you, they are ſpirit, and they are life.</p>
                     <p n="28">28.<note place="margin">16.</note> I came forth from the father, and am come into the world: againe I leaue the world, and go to my father.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. It is expedient for you, that I goe away; for if I goe not away, the comforter will not come vnto you: but if I depart, I will ſend him vnto you.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">14.</note> I goe to prepare a place for you.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And if I goe and <pb n="162" facs="tcp:565:97"/> prepare a place for you, I will come againe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you vnto my ſelfe, that where I am, there yee may be alſo.</p>
                     <p n="29">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note>29. I will not drinke henceforth of this fruite of the vine, vntill that day, when I drinke it new with you in my fathers king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
                     <p n="19">
                        <note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note>19. After the Lord had ſpoken to them, hee was receiued vp into heauen, and ſate on the right hand of God.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note>13. From henceforth expecting till his enemies be made his footſtoole.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. For by one offering <pb n="163" facs="tcp:565:97"/> he hath perfected for euer them that are ſanctified.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Col. 3.</note> If yee bee riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe things which are aboue, where Chriſt ſitteth on the right hand of God.</p>
                     <p n="20">20.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> Our conuerſation is in heauen, from whence alſo we looke for the Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="21">21.<note place="margin">Acts 3.</note> Whom the heauen muſt receiue vntill the times of reſtitution of all things, which God hath ſpoken by the mouth of all his holy Prophets ſince the world began.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="happiness" type="oracles">
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:565:98"/>
                     <head>The happineſſe of Gods ſeruants.</head>
                     <p n="37">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note>37. MArke the perfect man and behold the vpright; for the end of that man is peace.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">92.</note>12. The righteous ſhall flouriſh like the Palme tree: he ſhall grow like a Cedar in Lebanon.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">Hoſea 14.</note>6. His branches ſhall ſpread, and his beautie ſhall be as the Oliue tree; and his ſmell as Lebanon.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.</note>13. Thoſe that be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flouriſh in the Courts of our God.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <pb n="165" facs="tcp:565:98"/>14. They ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit in old age, they ſhall bee fat, and flouriſhing.</p>
                     <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">37.</note> The ſteps of a good man are ordered by the Lord; and he delighteth in his way.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Though he fall, he ſhall not vtterly bee caſt downe: for the Lord vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth him with his hand.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">25.</note> What man is hee that feareth the Lord? him ſhall hee reach in the way that he ſhall chooſe.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe, and his ſeed ſhall inherit the earth.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <pb n="166" facs="tcp:565:99"/>14. The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him, and hee will ſhew them his couenant.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal. 103.</note>17. The mercy of the Lord is from euerlaſting, to euerlaſting vpon them that feare him; and his righteouſneſſe vnto chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens children.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. To ſuch as keepe his couenant, and to thoſe that remember his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements to do them.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">65.</note>4. Bleſſed is the man whom thou chooſeſt and cauſeſt to approach vnto thee, that he may dwell in thy courts: he ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the goodneſſe
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:565:99"/> of thy houſe, euen of thy holy Temple.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="vanity" type="oracles">
                     <head>The vanitie of the world.</head>
                     <p n="15">15. LOue not the world,<note place="margin">1. Iohn
2.</note> neither the things that are in the world; if any man loue the world, the loue of the father is not in him.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. For all that is in the world, the luſt of the fleſh; the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. And the world paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away, and the luſt
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:565:100"/> thereof: but hee that doth the will of God abideth for euer.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note>14. I haue ſeene all the workes that are done vnder the Sun, and behold all is vanitie, and vexation of ſpirit.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Col. 3.</note>2. Set your affection on things aboue, not on things on the earth.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">Iames 4.</note>4. Whoſoeuer will be a friend of the world, is the enemie of God.</p>
                     <p n="24">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>24. No man can ſerue two maſters, for either hee will hate the one, and loue the other: or elſe he will hold to the one, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the other: ye cannot
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:565:100"/> God and Mammon.</p>
                     <p n="15">15.<note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> That which is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed amongſt men is abomination in the ſight of God.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. What is your life?<note place="margin">Iames.
4.</note> It is euen a vapor that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note> Man is like to vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, his dayes are as a ſhadow that paſſeth away.</p>
                     <p n="15">15.<note place="margin">103.</note> His dayes are as graſſe, as a flower of the field; ſo he floriſheth.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. For the winde paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ouer it, and it is gon: and the place thereof ſhall know it no more:</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Iob 14.</note> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forth like <pb n="170" facs="tcp:565:101"/> a flower and is cut downe; he flieth alſo as a ſhadow, and continueth not.</p>
                     <p n="24">
                        <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note>24. For all fleſh is as graſſe, and all the glorie of man as the flower of gras: the graſſe withereth, and the flower thereof falleth away.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 62.</note>9. Surely men of low degree are vanitie, and men of high degree are a lie: to be laid in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, they are altogether lighter then vanitie.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">39.</note>5. Verily euery man at his beſt ſtate is altogether vanitie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="end of the world" type="oracles">
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:565:101"/>
                     <head>The end of the world.</head>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> AS Ieſus ſate vpon the Mount of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues, the diſciples came vnto him priuately, ſaying, tell vs what ſhall bee the ſigne of thy comming? and of the end of the world?</p>
                     <p n="4">4. And Ieſus anſwered and ſaid vnto them; Take heede that no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. For many ſhall come in my name ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceiue many.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. And yee ſhall heare of warres, and rumors of
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:565:102"/> warres: See that yee bee not troubled; for all theſe things muſt come to paſſe, but the end is not yet.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">Math 24.</note>7. For nation ſhall riſe againſt nation, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againſt kingdome, and there ſhall be famines, and peſtilences, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes in diuers places.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. All theſe are but the beginning of ſorrowes.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Then ſhall they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you vp to be afflicted, and ſhall kill you: and yee ſhall bee hated of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for my names ſake.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. And they ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be offended, and ſhall betray one another, and <pb n="173" facs="tcp:565:102"/> ſhall hate one another.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. And many falſe prophets ſhall ariſe, and ſhall deceiue many.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. And becauſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie ſhall abound; the loue of many ſhall waxe cold.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. But hee that ſhall endure vnto the end ſhall be ſaued.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. And this Goſpell of the Kingdome ſhall be preached in all the world for a witneſſe vnto all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and then ſhall the end come.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. Then ſhall be great tribulation, ſuch as was not ſince the beginning of <pb n="174" facs="tcp:565:103"/> the world to this time, no not euer ſhall bee.</p>
                     <p n="22">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note>22. And except thoſe dayes ſhould bee ſhortned there ſhould no fleſh bee ſaued: but for the elects ſake, thoſe dayes ſhall bee ſhortned.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. There ſhall ariſe falſe chriſts, and falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and ſhal ſhew great ſignes, and wonders: in ſo much that if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they ſhall deceiue the very elect.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note>1. This know alſo that in the laſt dayes perilous times ſhall come.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. For men ſhall bee louers of their owne ſelues
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:565:103"/> couetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers, diſobedient to Parents, vnthankefull, vnholy.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Without naturall affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Traytors, heady, high minded, louers of pleaſures more then lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of God.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Hauing a forme of godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof, from ſuch turne away.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. For of this ſort are they which creepe into houſes, and leade captiue <pb n="176" facs="tcp:565:104"/> ſilly women, lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſins, led away with diuers luſts.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Euer learning, and neuer able to come to the knowledge of the truth.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8. Now as <hi>Iannes</hi> &amp; <hi>Iam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe alſo reſiſt the truth; men of corrupt mindes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate concerning faith.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. But they ſhall proceede no further: for their folly ſhall bee manifeſted vnto all men; as theirs alſo was.</p>
                     <p n="25">
                        <note place="margin">Luke 21.</note>25. And there ſhall be ſignes in the Sunne, and in the Moone, and in the ſtarres, and vpon the earth diſtreſſe of nations, with perplexitie, the ſea, and the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:565:104"/> waters ſhall roare.</p>
                     <p n="26">26. Mens heart fayling them for feare, and for looking after thoſe things which are comming on the earth; for the powers of heauen ſhal be ſhaken.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. And then ſhall they ſee the ſonne of man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in a cloude with power and great glory.</p>
                     <p n="28">28. And when theſe things ſhall begin to come to paſſe, then looke vp, and lift vp your heads for your redemption draweth nigh.</p>
                     <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">Mar. 13.</note> But of that day and houre knoweth no man, not the Angels in heauen, nor the ſon but the father.</p>
                     <p n="36">
                        <pb n="178" facs="tcp:565:105"/>
                        <note place="margin">Luke
21.</note>36. Watch yee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and pray alwayes that ye may be accounted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to eſcape all theſe things, that ſhall come to paſſe, and to ſtand before the ſonne of man.</p>
                     <p n="15">
                        <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note>15. For this we ſay, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you by the word of the Lord; that wee which are aliue, and remaine vnto the comming of the Lord, ſhall not preuent them which are aſleepe.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. For the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhall deſcend from heauen with a ſhoute, with the voice of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angel and with the trumpe of God: and the dead in <pb n="179" facs="tcp:565:105"/> Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. Then we which are aliue, and remaine, ſhall bee caught vp together with them in the clouds, to meete the Lord in the aire; and ſo ſhall we euer be with the Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="judgment" type="oracles">
                     <head>The Iudgement.</head>
                     <p n="27">27.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> IT is appointed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men to die; but after this the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Eccles. 12.</note> The duſt ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the earth as it was; and the ſpirit ſhall returne to God who gaue it.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> Wee know if our
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:565:106"/> earthly houſe of this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle were diſſolued; we haue a building of God, a houſe not made with hand, eternall in the heauens.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note>10. The bodie is dead becauſe of ſinne, but the ſpirit is life becauſe of righteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note>8. He that ſoweth to his fleſh ſhall of the fleſh reape corruption; but hee that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reape life euerlaſting.</p>
                     <p n="24">
                        <note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note>24. He that heareth my Word and beleeueth on him that ſent me, hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life, and ſhall
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:565:106"/> not come into condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but is paſſed from death vnto life.</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> The Lord knoweth the daies of the vpright; and their inheritance ſhall be for euer.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. But the wicked ſhall periſh, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Lord ſhall bee as the fat of lambes; they ſhall conſume; into ſmoke ſhall they conſume away.</p>
                     <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> The wages of ſinne is death, but the gift of GOD is eternall life tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. The begger died,<note place="margin">Luke 16</note> and was carried by the <pb n="182" facs="tcp:565:107"/> Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, the rich man alſo died, and was buried.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. And in hell hee lift vp his eyes being in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſeeth <hi>Abraham</hi> afarre off, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his boſome:</p>
                     <p n="24">24. And he cryed, and ſaid; father <hi>Abraham</hi> haue mercie on me, and ſend <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that hee may dip the tip of his finger in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and coole my tongue, for I am tormented in this flame.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. But <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, ſonne, remember that thou in thy life time recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uedſt thy good things, <pb n="183" facs="tcp:565:107"/> and likewiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> euill things; but now he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and thou art tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Wide is the gate,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> and broad is the way, that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there be which goe in thereat.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Straite is the gate, and narrow is the way, which leadeth vnto life, and few there bee that finde it.</p>
                     <p n="28">28.<note place="margin">Iohn 15.</note> The houre is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the which all that are in the graues, ſhall heare his voice.</p>
                     <p n="29">29. And ſhall come forth; they that haue done
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:565:108"/> good, vnto the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life; and they that haue done euill, vnto the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of damnation.</p>
                     <p n="46">
                        <note place="margin">Mat: 25.</note>46. Theſe ſhall goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into euerlaſting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: but the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous into life eternall.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Dan. 12.</note>2. Many of them that ſleepe in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake, ſome to euerlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting contempt.</p>
                     <p n="31">
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note>31. When the ſonne of man ſhall come in his glory, and ſhall the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with him, then ſhall hee ſit vpon the throne of his glory.</p>
                     <p n="32">
                        <pb n="185" facs="tcp:565:108"/>32.<note place="margin">Mat.
25.</note> And before him ſhall bee gathered all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and he ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as a ſheapheard diuideth his ſheepe from the goates.</p>
                     <p n="33">33. And he ſhall ſet the ſheepe on his right hand, but the goates on the left.</p>
                     <p n="34">34. Then ſhall the king ſay vnto them on his right hand, come yee bleſſed of my father, inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you from the foundation of the world.</p>
                     <p n="41">41. Then ſhall hee ſay vnto them on the left hand, depart from me yee curſed, into euerlaſting <pb n="186" facs="tcp:565:109"/> fire, prepared for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and his Angels.</p>
                     <p n="24">
                        <note place="margin">Iude.</note>24. Now vnto him that is able to keepe you from falling, and to preſent you faultleſſe, before the preſence of his glory with exceeding ioy.</p>
                     <p n="25">25. To the only wiſe God our Sauiour, be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and maieſtie, domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and power, now, and euer, Amen.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">Reuel 22.</note>14. Bleſſed are they that doe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that they may haue right to the tree of life, &amp; may enter in through the gates into the citie.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. For without are <pb n="187" facs="tcp:565:109"/> dogges, and ſorcerers, and whoremongers, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, and Idolaters, and whoſoeuer lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a lie.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:110"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:110"/>
                  <p>PSALTERIES OF THE HOLY GHOST</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ROM. 14 17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The Kingdome of GOD is not meate and drinke, but righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and peace, and ioy in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for E. BLACKMORE. 1628.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:111"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:111"/>
                  <head>A PREFACE concerning the PSALMES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAVID</hi> is ſaid to be the inſtrumentall cauſe of the Pſalmes, to whom all things were reuealed, and by him ſet downe Hee is alſo eſteemed the greater,<note place="margin">2. Samuel 23.2.</note> and more excellent Prophet, in that hee did not Propheſie by certaine viſions of things, or darke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerings of words, but by the inward motion onely of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: which is moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe the manifold and moſt beautifull riches in that <pb facs="tcp:565:112"/> treſurie conteined, are impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be matched by any other. Among which the inuocation of Almightie God (being the greateſt defence for our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, against the continuall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of Satan) is moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently compoſed for a preſedent, and direction vnto vs vpon all occaſions.<note place="margin">Eph.
6.18</note> We are commanded to pray alwayes, with all prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit, which is impoſſible for vs to do, vnleſſe we be learned in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Pietie, and guided therein by the holy Spirit of God. The true rule whereof is to be taken out of the Booke of the Pſalmes. For by reading them we are as well ſtirred vp to the vnderstanding of our infirmities, as admoniſhed and taught how to ſeeke a ſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie <pb facs="tcp:565:112"/> for them. They are doubtleſſe the Anatomie of all the parts of the ſoule: for wee cannot finde any diſpoſition or affection of the minde in our ſelues, the forme and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, is not in this glaſſe repreſented. When in this language we prepare our ſelues to ſpeake vnto God, we are drawne to ſo ſtrict an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that all our ſecret offences being diſcloſed, and our hearts cleanſed from hypocriſie, wee cannot but deliuer a reall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and full confeſſion of them. By this language (which is <hi>Verba ſpiritus ſancti,</hi> The words of the holy Ghost) wee haue not onely a familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto God, but do alſo find it more ſafe and auaileable for <pb facs="tcp:565:113"/> vs to acknowledge and confeſſe our ſinnes before him, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 1.9.</note> for he is faithfull and iust to forgiue vs our ſinnes, and to cleanſe vs from all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.8.</note> And it is better to truſt in him then to put confidence in man. In them wee haue examples and directions of thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing for bleſſings recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and dangers eſcaped. They are most comfortable in all times of temptation, trouble and affliction.</p>
                  <p>The Pſalmes therefore ought to be our meditations in all holy exerciſes, both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and publike; they are the key of knowledge. Almost all holy write and miſteries are briefely contained in them. Their ſcope is the right way <pb facs="tcp:565:113"/> to eternall felicitie.</p>
                  <p>Some of the Fathers do coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile the young ſouldiers of Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Caſſidor</note> firſt to learne them, before they learne the other holy Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>Others affirme that they are <hi>Arma Iuuenum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Climac. ex ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia Patrum.</note> The armour and weapons of young men; And I doubt not but they may alſo truely be accounted,
<hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaria ſenum;</hi> The armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and ſtorehouſes of old men. Another ſaith,<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
                     <hi>Liber Pſalmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quidvi, in ſe complectitur quod vſui ſit, &amp; omni. bonae doctrinae promptua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ium eſt;</hi> The booke of the Pſalmes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it whatſoeuer is vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and is the ſtorehouſe of all good doctrine. In them cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely is expreſſed as in a liuely reſemblance, the true
<pb facs="tcp:565:114"/> rule of religious ſeruice, and worſhip; for the example of a godly man aſſaulted by all manner of temptations, is of more power to moue, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs to flie vnto God, in time of neceſſitie, then a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement alone.<note place="margin">In proem. in 7. Pſal. poenitent.</note> 
                     <hi>INNOCENT</hi> the third ſaith; <hi>Inter omnes orationis ſpecies, poſt oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem dominicam, perfecta in Pſalmis forma orandi reperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Among all kinds of prayer, next vnto the Lords prayer, the abſolute forme of praying is ſound in the Pſalmes, yet not onely the words are to bee read, and rehearſed in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, but our hearts alſo must be attendant, and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto heauen; for wee are taught to lift vp our hands with our hearts vnto God in <pb facs="tcp:565:114"/> the heauens.</p>
                  <p>The holy Ghoſt being the dictator and guide of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids penne,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.41.</note> and tongue when they were by him regiſtred, It is most meete and requiſite, that in all times of our deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they bee recited with the aſſiſtance of the ſame bleſſed Spirit, which wee muſt before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand inuocate, lifting vp holy hands,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2 8.</note> without wrath or doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>AVGVSTINE</hi> in his laſt ſickneſſe appointed
<hi>DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIDS</hi> Penitentiall Pſalmes to be written,<note place="margin">Poſſidius in vita Auguſt.</note> and ſet vpon the foure ſides of the wall, which on his ſicke daies lying on his bed, he did behold and reade; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſhedding forth teares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly. S. <hi>BASIL</hi> alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his death bed, deſired <pb facs="tcp:565:115"/> that the Pſalmes might bee read vnto him by <hi>GREGO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE NAZIANZEN.</hi> A man certainely in his greateſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and anguiſh of conſcience occaſioned by Gods wrath, and iudgement, may by them learn to raiſe vp, and comfort him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Come then, let vs bring our offering of the fineſt gold to lay vpon Gods Altar, the leaſt graine whereof is more precious in his ſight, then all the Alcumie of the world. Let vs drinke of the pureſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and forſake the troubled and muddie riuers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.</note>Euery one that thirsteth, come ye to theſe waters, and he that hath no money, yea, come buy wine, and milke without money, and without price. Wherefore doe ye ſpend monie
<pb facs="tcp:565:115"/> for that which is not bread? and your labour for that which ſatisfieth not? Hearken dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently vnto the vndoubted te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies of our God, and eate ye that which is good, and let your ſoule delight it ſelfe in fatneſſe. Incline your eare, and come vnto him, heare, and your ſoule ſhall liue; and he will make an euerlasting couenant with you, euen the ſure mercies of <hi>DAVID.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="Psalter">
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:565:116"/>
                  <head>PSALTERIES OF THE HOLY GHOST.</head>
                  <div n="confession" type="Psalms">
                     <head>A Pſalme of Confeſsion.</head>
                     <p>VERSE</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note>1. <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto thee O LORD, doe I lift vp my ſoule.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">19.</note>14. Let the words of my mouth, and the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of my heart, be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in thy ſight, O Lord my ſtrength and my redeemer.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note>2. Hearken vnto the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:565:116"/> voice of my crye, my King and my God; for vnto thee will I pray.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note> For thou art not a God that hath pleaſure in wickedneſſe: neither ſhall euill dwell with thee.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">130.</note> If thou Lord ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt marke iniquities; O Lord who ſhall ſtand?</p>
                     <p n="4">4. But there is forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with thee, that thou mayſt be feared.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">86.</note> For thou Lord art good, and readie to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, and plenteous in mercy vnto all them that call vpon thee.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">69.</note> O God thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my fooliſhneſſe, and <pb n="202" facs="tcp:565:117"/> my ſinnes are not hid from thee.</p>
                     <p n="176">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>176. I haue gone aſtray like a loſt ſheepe; ſeeke thy ſeruant, for I doe not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thy commandements.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">51.</note>3. I acknowledge my tranſgreſſions, and my ſin is euer before me.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Againſt thee, thee onely haue I ſinned, and done this euil in thy ſight.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">38.</note>3. There is no ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in my fleſh becauſe of thine anger; neither is there any reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. For mine iniquities are gone ouer mine head; as an heauie burthen, they <pb n="203" facs="tcp:565:117"/> are two heauie for me.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. My wounds ſtinke, and are corrupt; becauſe of my fooliſhneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.</note> Innumerable euils haue compaſſed me, mine iniquities haue taken hold vpon me, ſo that I am not able to looke vp. They are more then the haires of mine head; therefore mine heart faileth me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="contrition" type="Psalms">
                     <head>Of Contrition.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note> O Lord rebuke me not in thy wrath: neither chaſten me in thy hot diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleaſure.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. For thine arrowes <pb n="204" facs="tcp:565:118"/> ſticke faſt in me, and thy hand preſſeth me ſore.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note>6. I am troubled, I am bowed downe greatly, I go mourning all the day long.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">22.</note>14. I am powred out like water, and all my bones are out of ioynt: my heart is like waxe, it is mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the middeſt of my bowels.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">31.</note>12. I am forgotten as a dead man out of mind: I am like a broken veſſell.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">41.</note>4. Lord bee mercifull vnto me; heale my ſoule, for I haue ſinned againſt thee.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">38.</note>9. All my deſire is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb n="205" facs="tcp:565:118"/> thee: and my groaning is not hid from thee.</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note> For I will declare mine iniquitie; I will bee ſorie for my ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="17">17.<note place="margin">51.</note> The ſacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit; A broken &amp; a contrite heart ô God thou wilt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe:</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">51.</note> Make me to heare ioy and gladneſſe, that the bones which thou haſt broken may reioyce.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Create in mee a cleane heart, and renew a right ſpirit within me.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Caſt me not away from thy preſence, and take not thy holy ſpirit <pb n="206" facs="tcp:565:119"/> from me.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>12. Reſtore to me the ioy of thy ſaluation; and vphold me with thy free ſpirit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="remission" type="Psalms">
                     <head>For Remiſsion.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>1. HAue mercie vpon me O God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy louing kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: according to the multitude of thy tender mercies blot out my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Waſh me throughly from mine iniquitie, and cleanſe me from my ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Purge mee with Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop, and I ſhall be cleane:
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:565:119"/> waſh mee, and I ſhall bee whiter then ſnow.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.</note> For thy names ſake O Lord pardon mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, for it is great.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Remember not the ſinnes of my youth, nor my tranſgreſſions: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy mercy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thou me, for thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake ô Lord.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Turne thee vnto me and haue mercy vpon me, for I am deſolate and afflicted.</p>
                     <p n="18">18 Looke vpon mine affliction, and my paine; and forgiue all my ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. O keepe my ſoule and deliuer me; let me not
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:565:120"/> bee aſhamed, for I put my truſt in thee.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note>8. Deliuer me from all my tranſgreſſions, make me not the reproch of the fooliſh.</p>
                     <p n="16">
                        <note place="margin">31.</note>16. Make thy face to ſhine vpon thy ſeruant, ſaue mee for thy mercies ſake.</p>
                     <p n="9">
                        <note place="margin">51.</note>9. Hide thy face from my ſinnes, and blot out all mine iniquities.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">141.</note>8. Mine eyes are vnto thee ô Lord God, in thee is my truſt: leaue not my ſoule deſtitute.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="mercy" type="Psalms">
                     <pb n="209" facs="tcp:565:120"/>
                     <head>For mercy and direction.</head>
                     <p n="16">16. HEare me ô Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal.
69.</note> for thy louing kindneſſe is good, Turne vnto me according to the multitude of thy tender mercies.</p>
                     <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">25.</note> Remember ô Lord thy tender mercies and thy louing kindneſſe; for they haue beene euer of old.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">27.</note> Hide not thy face from mee, put not thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant away in anger; thou haſt beene my helpe, leaue me not, neither forſake me, O God of my ſaluation.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="210" facs="tcp:565:121"/>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal. 86.</note>3. Bee mercifull vnto me O Lord, for I crie vnto thee dayly.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">25.</note>4. Shew me thy waies O Lord, teach mee thy pathes.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Leade mee in thy truth and teach mee, for thou art the God of my ſaluation, on thee doe I waite all the day.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">43.</note>2. For thou art the God of my ſtrength, why doeſt thou caſt me off? why goe I mourning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the oppreſſion of the enemie?</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">43.</note>3. O ſend out thy light and thy truth, let them leade mee; let them bring <pb n="211" facs="tcp:565:121"/> me vnto thy holy hill, and thy tabernacles.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.</note> Cauſe me to heare thy louing kindneſſe in the morning for in thee doe I truſt: Cauſe mee to know the way wherein I ſhould walke, for I lift vp my ſoule vnto thee.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Teach mee to doe thy will for thou art my God, thy ſpirit is good: leade mee into the land of vprightneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.<note place="margin">40.</note> Withhold not thou thy tender mercies from mee O Lord; Let thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe and thy truth continually preſerue me</p>
                     <p n="133">
                        <pb n="212" facs="tcp:565:122"/>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal. 119.</note>133. Order my ſteps in thy Word, and let not any iniquitie haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer me.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">86.</note>11. Teach me thy way O Lord, I will walke in thy truth, vnite my heart to feare thy name.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">39.</note>4. Lord make mee to know mine end, and the meaſure of my dayes what it is, that I may know how fraile I am.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="understanding" type="Psalms">
                     <head>For vnderſtanding</head>
                     <p n="169">
                        <note place="margin">119.</note>169. LEt my crie come neere before thee O Lord, giue me vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding according to thy Word.</p>
                     <p n="26">
                        <pb n="213" facs="tcp:565:122"/>26.<note place="margin">Pſal.
119</note> I haue declared my wayes, and thou heardeſt me; teach me thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
                     <p n="27">27. Make me to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the way of thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts; ſo ſhall I talke of thy woundrous workes.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. Open thou mine eyes, that I may behold the wounderous things out of thy Law.</p>
                     <p n="73">73. Thy hands haue made mee and faſhioned me; giue me vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that I may learne thy commandements.</p>
                     <p n="41">41. Let thy mercies come alſo vnto me, O Lord, euen thy ſaluation, <pb n="214" facs="tcp:565:123"/> according to thy Word.</p>
                     <p n="77">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 119</note>77. Let thy tender mercies come vnto mee, that I may liue, for thy Law is my delight.</p>
                     <p n="175">
                        <note place="margin">119.</note>175. Let my ſoule liue and it ſhall praiſe thee; and let thy iudgements helpe me.</p>
                     <p n="156">156. Great are thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies O LORD; quicken me according to thy iudgements.</p>
                     <p n="144">144. The righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy teſtimonies is euerlaſting: giue mee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and I ſhall liue.</p>
                     <p n="160">160. Thy word is truth from the beginning; and
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:565:123"/> euerie one of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgements endureth for euer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="trouble" type="Psalms">
                     <head>In trouble.</head>
                     <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> HAue mercie vpon me, O Lord, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider my trouble which I ſuffer of them that hate me: thou that lifteſt mee vp from the gates of death.</p>
                     <p n="12">12.<note place="margin">10.</note> Ariſe O Lord lift vp thy hand; forget not the humble.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.<note place="margin">22.</note> Bee not farre from me, for trouble is neere, for there is none to helpe.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">31.</note> In the O Lord doe I
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:565:124"/> put my truſt, let me neuer be aſhamed: deliuer mee in thy righteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note>2. Bow downe thine eare vnto me, deliuer me ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily: be thou my ſtrong rocke for an houſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to ſaue me.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. For thou art my rocke and my fortreſſe: Therefore for thy names ſake lead me, &amp; guide me.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Turne thee vnto me,<note place="margin">25.</note> and haue mercie vpon me; for I am deſolate, and afflicted.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. The troubles of mine heart are enlarged: O bring me out of my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes.</p>
                     <p n="18">
                        <pb n="217" facs="tcp:565:124"/>18.<note place="margin">Pſal.
25.</note> Looke vpon mine affliction, and my paine; and forgiue all my ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. O Keepe my ſoule, and deliuer me: Let me not be aſhamed, for I put my truſt in thee.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. Let integritie, and vprightneſſe preſerue me; for I waite on thee.</p>
                     <p n="15">15.<note place="margin">25.</note> Mine eyes are euer towards the Lord; for hee ſhall plucke my feete out of the net.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="deliverance" type="Psalms">
                     <head>For deliuerance.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. SAue me O God,<note place="margin">69.</note> for the waters are come in vnto my ſoule.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="218" facs="tcp:565:125"/>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal.
69.</note>2. I ſinke in deepe mire, where there is no ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: I am come into deep waters, where the floods ouerflow me.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. My prayer is to thee O Lord in an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table time, O God in the multitude of thy mercie heare me, in the truth of thy ſaluation.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Deliuer mee out of the mire, and let mee not ſinke: let mee be deliuered from them that hate mee, and out of the deepe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Let not the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flood ouerflow mee, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let the deepe ſwallow <pb n="219" facs="tcp:565:125"/> me vp: and let not the pit ſhut her mouth vpon me.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Heare me o Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal.
69.</note> for thy louing kindneſſe is good; turne vnto mee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of thy tender mercies.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. And hide not thy face from thy ſeruant, for I am in trouble; heare mee ſpeedily.</p>
                     <p n="33">33. The Lord heareth the poore, and deſpiſeth not his priſoners.</p>
                     <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">72.</note> He ſhall deliuer the needie, when hee cryeth: the poore alſo, and him that hath no helper.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">70.</note> I am poore and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, make haſt vnto me O <pb n="220" facs="tcp:565:126"/> God: thou art my helpe and my deliuerer, O Lord make no tarrying.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 71.</note>2. Deliuer mee in thy righteouſneſſe and cauſe me to eſcape: incline thine eare vnto mee, and ſaue me.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Bee thou my ſtrong habitation, whereunto I may continually reſort: thou haſt given comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to ſaue mee, for thou art my recke and my fortreſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="enemies" type="Psalms">
                     <head>Againſt our enemies.</head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">35.</note>1. PLeade my cauſe O Lord with them <pb n="221" facs="tcp:565:126"/> that ſtriue with me: fight againſt them that fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Pſal. 35.</note> Take hold of ſhield and buckler, and ſtand vp for my helpe.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Draw out alſo the ſpeare, and ſtop the way againſt them that perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute me: ſay vnto my ſoule, I am thy ſaluation.</p>
                     <p n="23">23.<note place="margin">35.</note> Stirre vp thy ſelfe and awake to my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: euen vnto my cauſe my God and my Lord.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">59.</note> Deliuer mee from mine enemies. O Lord my God: defend mee from them that riſe vp againſt me.</p>
                     <p n="25">
                        <pb n="222" facs="tcp:565:127"/>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſal. 36.</note>25. Let them not ſay in their hearts, Ah, ſo would we haue it; let them not ſay, we haue ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him vp.</p>
                     <p n="20">
                        <note place="margin">9.</note>20. Put them in feare O Lord; that the nations may know themſelues to be but men.</p>
                     <p n="29">
                        <note place="margin">109.</note>29. Let mine aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries bee cloathed with ſhame, and let them couer themſelues with their owne confuſion, as with a mantle.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <note place="margin">5.</note>11. But let all thoſe that put their truſt in thee reioyce, let them euer ſhout for ioy, becauſe thou defendeſt them; let <pb n="223" facs="tcp:565:127"/> them alſo that loue thy name, be ioyfull in thee.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Pſal. 138</note> Though I walke in the middeſt of trouble thou wilt receiue me; thou ſhalt ſtretch forth thine hand againſt the wrath of mine enemies, and thy right hand ſhall ſaue me.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">7.</note> O Lord my God in thee doe I put my truſt; ſaue me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute me, &amp; deliuer me.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Leade mee O Lord,<note place="margin">5.</note> in thy righteouſneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of mine enemies: Make thy waies ſtraight before my face.</p>
                     <p n="28">28.<note place="margin">35.</note> And my tongue ſhall ſpeake of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: <pb n="224" facs="tcp:565:128"/> and of thy praiſe all the day long.</p>
                     <p n="14">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 71.</note>14. I will hope conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and will yet prayſe thee more and more.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. My mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thy ſaluation all the day, for I know no numbers thereof.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. I will goe in the ſtrength of the Lord God: I will make mention of thy righteouſneſſe, euen of thine onely.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">18.</note>3. I will call vpon the Lord, who is worthy to be praiſed: ſo ſhall I be ſaued from mine enemies.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">84.</note>12. O Lord of Hoſts:
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:565:128"/> Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="confidence in mercy" type="Psalms">
                     <head>Of confidence in Gods mercie.</head>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> THe Lord is my ſhepheard; I ſhall not want.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He maketh me to lie downe in greene paſtures: Hee leadeth me beſide the ſtill waters.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Hee reſtoreth my ſoule, he leadeth me in the pathes of righteouſneſſe for his names ſake.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Yea though I walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will feare none euill; for thou <pb n="226" facs="tcp:565:129"/> art with me, thy red, and thy ſtaffe, they comfort me.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 61.</note>4. I will abide in thy tabernacle for euer: I will truſt in the couert of thy wings.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Becauſe thou haſt beene my helpe; therefore in the ſhadow of thy wings will I reioyce.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">61.</note>3. For thou haſt beene a ſhelter for me, and a ſtrong tower from mine enemies.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">71.</note>5. Thou art my hope, O Lord God: Thou art my truſt from my youth.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">35.</note>7. Thou art my hiding place, thou ſhalt preſerue me from trouble; thou <pb n="227" facs="tcp:565:129"/> ſhalt compaſſe me about with ſongs of deliuerance.</p>
                     <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.</note> I will come into thy houſe in the multitude of thy mercie: and in thy feare will I worſhippe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thine holy temple.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. For thou Lord wilt bleſſe the righteous, with fauour wilt thou compaſſe him as with a ſhield.</p>
                     <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">16.</note> I haue ſet the Lord alwayes before mee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is at my right hand, I ſhall not bee moued.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">62.</note> My ſoule waite thou onely vpon GOD, for my expectation is from him.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="228" facs="tcp:565:130"/>6. He onely is my rocke, and my ſaluation: hee is my defence I ſhall not bee moued.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <note place="margin">40.</note>4. Bleſſed is that man that maketh the Lord his truſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="acknowledging mercy" type="Psalms">
                     <head>Acknowledging Gods mercie.</head>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 28.</note>7. THe Lord is my ſtrength, and my ſhield, my heart truſted in him, and I am helped: therefore my heart great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reioyceth and with my ſong will I praiſe him.</p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <note place="margin">86.</note>12. I will praiſe thee O Lord my God, with all my <pb n="229" facs="tcp:565:130"/> heart; and I will glorifie thy name for euermore.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. For great is thy mercy towards mee, and thou haſt deliuered my ſoule from the loweſt hell.</p>
                     <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>3.</note> In the day when I cried thou anſweredſt me; and ſtrengthenedſt mee with ſtrength in my ſoule.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">32.</note> I acknowledged my ſinne vnto thee, and mine iniquitie I haue not hid.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. I ſaid I will confeſſe my tranſgreſſions vnto the Lord, and thou forga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt the iniquitie of my ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="11">11.<note place="margin">16.</note> Thou wilt ſhew me the path of life, in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence <pb n="230" facs="tcp:565:131"/> is fullneſſe of ioy, at thy right hand there are pleaſures for euermore.</p>
                     <p n="32">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note>32. It is God that gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth mee with ſtrength; and maketh my way per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
                     <p n="31">31. For who is God ſaue the Lord? or who is a rocke ſaue our God?</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <note place="margin">147.</note>3. He healeth the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in heart, and bindeth vp their wounds.</p>
                     <p n="22">
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>4.</note>22. The Lord redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſoule of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: and none of them that truſt in him ſhall bee deſolate.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <note place="margin">145.</note>8. The Lord is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and full of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <pb n="231" facs="tcp:565:131"/> ſlow to anger, and of great mercie.</p>
                     <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> The Lord is good to all; and his tender mercies are ouer all his works.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. All thy workes praiſe thee, O Lord, and thy Saints bleſſe thee.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. They ſhall ſpeake of the glorie of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and talke of thy power.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Thy Kingdome is an euerlaſting Kingdome, and thy dominion endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth throughout all ages.</p>
                     <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">36.</note> Thy mercie O Lord is in the heauens, and thy faithfullneſſe reacheth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Clouds.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="232" facs="tcp:565:132"/>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal.
36.</note>6. Thy righteouſneſſe is like the great moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp; thy iudgements are a great deepe, O Lord thou preſerueſt man and beaſt.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. How excellent is thy louing kindneſſe O God? therefore the children of men put their truſt vnder the ſhadow of thy wings.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. They ſhall be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thy houſe: and thou ſhalt make them drinke of the riuers of thy pleaſures.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. For with thee is the well of life: and in thy light ſhall we ſee light.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="magnifying mercy" type="Psalms">
                     <pb n="233" facs="tcp:565:132"/>
                     <head>Magnifying Gods mercie and goodneſſe.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. I will praiſe thee,<note place="margin">Pſal.
9.</note> O Lord with my whole heart; I will ſhew foorth all thy maruelous workes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. I will be glad and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in thee, I will ſing praiſe vnto thy name, ô thou moſt high.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. They that know thy name, will put their truſt in thee; for thou Lord haſt not forſaken them that ſeeke thee.</p>
                     <p n="90">90.<note place="margin">119.</note> Thy faithfulneſſe is to all generations: thou haſt eſtabliſhed the earth
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:565:133"/> and it abideth.</p>
                     <p n="142">
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>142. Thy righteouſneſſe is an euerlaſting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; and thy Law is truth.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <note place="margin">135.</note>13. Thy Name, ô Lord endureth for euer; and thy memoriall ô Lord tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out all generations.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">106.</note>2. Who can vtter the mightie acts of the Lord? Who can ſhew forth all his praiſe?</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <note place="margin">33.</note>5. Hee loueth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and iudgement; The earth is full of the goodneſſe of the Lord.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <note place="margin">111.</note>7. The workes of his hands are veritie, and iudgement; all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements <pb n="235" facs="tcp:565:133"/> are true.</p>
                     <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 111.</note> Hee hath made his wonderfull works to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred: The Lord is gracious and full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</p>
                     <p n="14">14.<note place="margin">145.</note> The Lord vpholdeth all that fall; and raiſeth vp all thoſe that bee bowed downe.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. He will fullfill the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſire of them that feare him; Hee will alſo heare their crie, and ſaue them.</p>
                     <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">103.</note> Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe the Lord O my ſoule: and all that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me bleſſe his holy name.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Bleſſe the Lord ô my ſoule: and forget not all his benefits.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="236" facs="tcp:565:134"/>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal.
103.</note>3. Who forgiueth all thine iniquities; who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all thy diſeaſes.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Who redeemeth thy life from deſtruction; who crowneth thee with louing kindeneſſe, and tender mercies.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <note place="margin">113.</note>2. Bleſſed be the name of the Lord: from this time forth for euermore.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="praise" type="Psalms">
                     <head>Of Praiſe.</head>
                     <p n="33">
                        <note place="margin">104.</note>33. I will ſing vnto the Lord as long as I liue: I will ſing praiſe vnto my God whiles I haue any being.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <note place="margin">7.</note>17. I will praiſe the
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:565:134"/> Lord, according to his righteouſneſſe: I will ſing praiſe vnto the name of the Lord moſt high.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. O Lord our Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> how excellent is thy name in all the earth; who haſt ſet thy glory aboue the heauens?</p>
                     <p n="18">18.<note place="margin">35.</note> I will giue thee thankes in the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I will praiſe thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong much people.</p>
                     <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">138.</note> I will worſhippe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy holy Temple, and praiſe thy name for thy louing kindneſſe, and for thy truth: for thou haſt magnified thy word aboue all thy name.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="238" facs="tcp:565:135"/>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal.
145.</note>1. I will extoll thee my God, O king; and I will bleſſe thy name for euer and euer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Euery day will I bleſſe thee, and I will praiſe thy name for euer and euer.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. My mouth ſhall ſpeake the praiſe of the Lord, and let all fleſh bleſſe his holy name for euer and euer.</p>
                     <p n="46">
                        <note place="margin">18.</note>46. The Lord liueth, and bleſſed bee my rocke; and let the God of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation be exalted.</p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <note place="margin">28.</note>6. Bleſſed be the Lord, becauſe he hath heard the voice of my ſupplications.</p>
                     <p n="13">
                        <pb n="239" facs="tcp:565:135"/>13.<note place="margin">Pſal.
41.</note> Bleſſed be the Lord GOD of Iſrael from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:136"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:136"/>
                  <p>PSALMES IN SICKNESSE.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>IAMES 5.15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>The prayer of faith ſhall ſaue the ſicke, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him vp: and if he haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſins, they ſhall be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen him.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for E. BLACKMORE. 1628.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="Psalm">
                  <pb n="242" facs="tcp:565:137"/>
                  <head>THE FIRST PSALME IN SICKNESSE.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note>1. O Lord rebuke mee not in thy wrath, neither chaſten mee in thy hot diſpleaſure.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For thine arrowes ſticke faſt in me; and thy hand preſſeth me ſore.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is no ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in my fleſh, becauſe of thine anger; neither is there any reſt in my bones, becauſe of my ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <pb n="243" facs="tcp:565:137"/>14.<note place="margin">Pſal.
22.</note> I am powred out like water, &amp; all my bones are out of ioynt: My heart is like waxe, it is melted in the middeſt of my bowells.</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">38.</note> For mine iniquities are gone ouer my head; as an heauie burthen they are too heauy for me.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. My wounds ſtinke &amp; are corrupt, becauſe of my fooliſhneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">41.</note> Lord bee mercifull vnto me, heale my ſoule; for I haue ſinned againſt thee.</p>
                  <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">38.</note> All my deſire is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; and my groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not hid from thee.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. For I will declare <pb n="244" facs="tcp:565:138"/> mine iniquitie; and will be ſorry for my ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="176">
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>176. I haue gone aſtray like a loſt ſheepe: ſeeke thy ſeruant, for I do not forget thy Commandements.</p>
                  <p n="175">175. Let my ſoule liue, and it ſhall praiſe thee: and let thy iudgements helpe me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="Psalm">
                  <head>Second Pſalme.</head>
                  <p n="16">
                     <note place="margin">69.</note>16. HEare me ô Lord for thy louing kindneſſe is good: Turne vnto me according to the multitude of thy tender mercies.</p>
                  <p n="18">
                     <note place="margin">25.</note>18. Looke vpon mine
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:565:138"/> affliction, and my paine; and forgiue all my ſinnes.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. O keepe my ſoule,<note place="margin">Pſal.
25.</note> and deliuer me: let me not be aſhamed, for I put my truſt in thee.</p>
                  <p n="28">28.<note place="margin">119.</note> My ſoule melteth for heauineſſe; ſtrengthen me according to thy word.</p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">51.</note> Waſh me throughly from mine iniquitie: and cleanſe me from my ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. For I acknowledge my tranſgreſſions: and my ſinne is euer before me.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Purge me with Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſope, and I ſhall be cleane: Waſh me, and I ſhall bee whiter then ſnow.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Make mee to heare <pb n="246" facs="tcp:565:139"/> ioy and gladneſſe; that the bones which thou haſt broken may reioyce.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 142.</note>5. Thou art my refuge, and my portion in the land of the liuing.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <note place="margin">31.</note>16. Make thy face to ſhine vpon thy ſeruant; ſaue mee for thy mercies ſake.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="Psalm">
                  <head>Third Pſalme.</head>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin">6.</note>2. HAue mercy vpon me ô Lord, for I am weake; ô Lord helpe me for my bones are vexed.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <note place="margin">69.</note>3. I am weary of crying, my throat is dryed, mine eyes faile while I waite for my God</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <pb n="247" facs="tcp:565:139"/>11.<note place="margin">Pſal.
51.</note> Caſt me not away from thy preſence, &amp; take not thy holy ſpirit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Reſtore to mee the ioy of thy ſaluation: and vphold mee with thy free ſpirit.</p>
                  <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">17.</note> Keepe me as the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the eye: hide me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of thy wings.</p>
                  <p n="94">94. I am thine ſaue me;<note place="margin">119.</note> for I haue ſought thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
                  <p n="174">174. I haue longed for thy ſaluation O Lord; and thy law is my delight.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. My ſoule,<note place="margin">62.</note> waite thou onely vp in God; for my expectation is from him.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="248" facs="tcp:565:140"/>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal. 62.</note>6. He only is my Rocke, and my ſaluation: he is my defence, I ſhall not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <note place="margin">40.</note>4. Bleſſed is that man, that maketh the Lord his truſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="Psalm">
                  <head>Fourth Pſalme.</head>
                  <p n="5">
                     <note place="margin">42.</note>5. VVHy art thou caſt downe O my ſoule? and why art thou diſquieted within mee? Hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him who is the health of my counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and my God.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">27.</note>1. The Lord is my light, and my ſaluation, whom <pb n="249" facs="tcp:565:140"/> ſhall I feare? The Lord is the ſtrength of my life, of whom ſhall I be afraid?</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> Though I walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will feare none euill: for thou art with mee, thy rod and thy ſtaffe they comfort me.</p>
                  <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">13.</note> I haue truſted in thy mercy, my heart ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in thy ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="19">19.<note place="margin">31.</note> O how great is thy goodnes which thou haſt layd vp for them that feare thee? which thou haſt wrought for them that truſt in thee, before the ſonnes of men?</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="250" facs="tcp:565:141"/>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal.
36.</note>7. How excellent is thy louing kindneſſe O Lord? Therefore the children of men put their truſt vnder the ſhadow of thy wings.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. With thee is the fountaine of life, and in thy light ſhall we ſee light.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <note place="margin">145.</note>9. The Lord is good to all, and his tender mercies are ouer all his workes.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <note place="margin">66.</note>8. O bleſſe our God yee people, and make the voyce of his praiſe to bee heard.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin">103.</note>2. Bleſſe the Lord O my ſoule; and forget not all his benefits.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Who forgiueth all thine iniquitie; who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:565:141"/> all thy diſeaſes.</p>
                  <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> Who redeemeth thy life from deſtruction; and crowneth thee with louing kindneſſe and tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
                  <p n="13">13.<note place="margin">41.</note> Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, to euerlaſting.</p>
                  <trailer>Amen, Amen.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="252" facs="tcp:565:142"/>
                  <head>A PRAYER.</head>
                  <p n="17">
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.</note>17. THe GOD of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Father of glory, giue vnto you the ſpirit of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and reuelation in the knowledge of him.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. That the eyes of your vnderſtanding being inlightened, you may know, what is the hope of his calling, and what the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the glory of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in the Saints.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. And what is the exceeding greatneſſe of his power to vs-ward that beleeue, according to the <pb n="253" facs="tcp:565:142"/> working of his mightie power.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Which he wrought in Chriſt, when hee raiſed him from the dead, and ſet him on his owne right hand, in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly place.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Farre aboue all Principalitie, and power, and might, and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and euery name that is named, not onely in this world, but alſo in that which is to come.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. And hath put all things vnder his feete, and gaue him to be head ouer all things to the Church;</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Which is his body; the fulneſſe of him that fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all in all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="254" facs="tcp:565:143"/>
                  <head>The Soules comfort.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AS by the ſacred Fountaine I did paſſe,</l>
                     <l>The ſtreames ſent forth ſuch pleaſant melody;</l>
                     <l>That, with deep ſighs, my ſoule cryd out,
<hi>Alas</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Why ſhould I wander from this harmony?</l>
                     <l>The ſound wherof guides to eternall bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>Diuerting from thoſe pathes which leade amiſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The warbling notes reſounded ſtill and ſaid,</l>
                     <l>Oft haſt thou fallen by thine iniquitie:</l>
                     <l>Yet lift thy heart to heauen, be not afraid,</l>
                     <l>Repentance is a conſtant remedie.</l>
                     <l>Then ſearch and try thy wayes, returne, and know,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſcarlet deeds ſhall be as white as ſnow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If thou confeſſe thou haſt peruerted right,</l>
                     <l>Yet no aduantage haſt thereby obtay'nd:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="255" facs="tcp:565:143"/>Thy ſoule ſhall liue, thy life ſhal ſee the light,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſinnes ſeeme wooll, which were with crimſon ſtayn'd.</l>
                     <l>A light is come, and darkeneſſe vaniſhed:</l>
                     <l>Beleeue in him alone that promiſed.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Afflicted widowes and the fatherleſſe</l>
                     <l>To viſit, is a worke of charitie;</l>
                     <l>The poore to helpe, and ſuch as in diſtreſſe</l>
                     <l>Want comfort to relieue their miſerie.</l>
                     <l>Yet pleade not merit in thy loſt account;</l>
                     <l>Truſt to that mercy which doth al ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Still doſt thou violate the ſacred lawes,</l>
                     <l>And iuſtly heapeſt wrath vpon thine head:</l>
                     <l>Yet haſt an aduo ate to pleade thy cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Who onely hath the power to interceade.</l>
                     <l>He euer liues at the tribun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll ſeate,</l>
                     <l>Mercy for our offences to intreate.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When neither ſiluer, gold, nor earthly price</l>
                     <l>Could vs redeem, and purge our hainous ſin:</l>
                     <l>He ſhed his bloud, his life did ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>That for vs which were loſt, he heauen might winne</l>
                     <l>He lou'd vs, though his ſtatutes we forgot,</l>
                     <l>And ſuffered for our ſinnes; yet had no ſpot.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:565:144"/>
                     <l>He craues no meed for all that he hath done,</l>
                     <l>But with our hearts to feare, to ſerue to loue him:</l>
                     <l>His glory is, <hi>from death he hath vs wonne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That we may know there is no power aboue him.</l>
                     <l>Then let vs ſtriue to walke in all his wayes;</l>
                     <l>And in all things to giue his name the praiſe</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And euer liſten to thoſe heauenly ſtreames,</l>
                     <l>Which yeild ſuch muſick for the ſouls delight:</l>
                     <l>Abandoning all mens deceitfull dreames,</l>
                     <l>Who through their pride obſcure the cleareſt light</l>
                     <l>Cloſe by this fountaine I reſolue to dwell,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe warbles doe all humane art excell.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:144"/>
                  <head>Errata.</head>
                  <p>Page 6. Line 6. reade the for thy. p. 13 l 1 r. Ia 1. for Iſa.
1 and 21. for 16 p. 44. l. 8 r. from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you. p. 65. l. 10. r. ruine. for raigne &amp; l. 19 dele ye. p. 112. l. 18. r in the Synagogues p. 117. l. 8. dele Sanctuary p. 149. l. 4 r. make you perfect.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:145" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:145"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:146" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:565:146" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
